<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The charge of God and the King to iudges and magistrates, for execution of iustice. In a sermon preached before Sr Henry Hobart Knight and Baronet, Lord Chiefe Iustice of the Common Pleas: and Sr Robert Haughton Knight, one of the iudges of the Kings Bench, at the Assises at Hartford. By William Pemberton B.D. and minister at high-Ongar in Essex.</title>
            <author>Pemberton, William, d. 1622.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 151 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 65 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09254</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19568</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103437</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839190</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839190</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3592</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09254)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3592)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1251:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The charge of God and the King to iudges and magistrates, for execution of iustice. In a sermon preached before Sr Henry Hobart Knight and Baronet, Lord Chiefe Iustice of the Common Pleas: and Sr Robert Haughton Knight, one of the iudges of the Kings Bench, at the Assises at Hartford. By William Pemberton B.D. and minister at high-Ongar in Essex.</title>
                  <author>Pemberton, William, d. 1622.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20], 108 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Edward Griffin for Samuel Man, dvvelling in Paules church-yard at the signe of the Svvan,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1619.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Pages 77, 80-81, 84-85, 88-89, 92, and 97 misnumbered 61, 64-65, 68-69, 72-73, 76 and 67.</note>
                  <note>Some print faded and show-through, and some pages stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3592:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3592:1"/>
            <p>THE CHARGE OF <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>King,</hi> To Iudges and Magiſtrates, <hi>for execution of Iuſtice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a Sermon preached before S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> HENRY HOBART Knight and Baronet, Lord Chiefe Iuſtice of the Common Pleas: and S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> ROBERT HAVGHTON Knight, one of the Iudges of the Kings Bench, <hi>At the Aſſiſes at Hartford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>William Pemberton</hi> B. D. and <hi>Miniſter at high-Ongar in Eſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 CHRON. 19.6, 7.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>6.</hi> And he (Jehoſaphat) ſaid to the Judges. Take heed what yee do: for yee iudge not for man, but for the Lord, who is with you in the iudgment.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <hi>7.</hi> Wherefore now, let the feare of the Lord be vpon you, take heed and do it: for there is no iniquitie with the Lord our God, nor reſpect of perſons, nor taking of gifts.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>Edward Griffin</hi> for <hi>Samuel Man,</hi> dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in Paules Church-yard at the ſigne of the Swan. 1619.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:3592:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3592:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE FRANCIS LORD VERVLAM, Lord Chancellor of England, one of his Maieſties moſt honorable <hi>Priuie Councell.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">AND TO THE REVEREND Iudges, and worthy Magiſtrates: <hi>the ſpirit of wiſdome, counſell, and feare of the Lord.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE wiſdom of God doth thus profeſſe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime to the ſonnes of men;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 8.15, 16.</note> 
               <hi>By mee Kings raigne &amp; Princes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree iuſtice. By mee Princes rule and Nobles, euen all the Iudges of the earth.</hi> Hereby giuing man to wit, that <hi>the higher powers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1.</note> or
<pb facs="tcp:3592:3"/>eminency of authoritie, and <hi>order</hi> of magiſtracy, ſupreme and ſubordinate,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 2.13.</note> is the <hi>ordination</hi> of God. Which how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer it be called an <hi>ordinance of Man</hi> in reſpect either <hi>1.</hi> of Man the ſubiect, by whom it is exerciſed. or <hi>2.</hi> of Man the obiect, about whom it is converſant. or <hi>3.</hi> of Man, the end to whoſe good it tendeth; yet is ſtill the gift and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of God, the primary author and prouident ordeiner. <hi>For there is no power,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1.</note> 
               <hi>but of God: The powers that be are ordeined of God,</hi> to which ſubmiſsion muſt be yeelded by inferiors for <hi>conſcience</hi> ſake to God.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 5.</note> Which well-ground Maxime whoſoeuer ſhall denie, he is worthy to be thruſt out with <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> to liue among beaſts,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan:</hi> 4.32.</note> (vnworthy the ſociety of men) vntill he <hi>know that the moſt High ruleth in the kingdome of men, and giueth it to whomſoeuer he will. He that is higher than the higheſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.8.</note> the <hi>King of Kings, and Lord of Lords,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.15.</note> the moſt mighty <hi>Creator</hi> and moſt wiſe <hi>diſpoſer</hi> of all things,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.21.</note> 
               <hi>who remoueth Kings
<pb facs="tcp:3592:3"/>and ſetteth vp Kings,</hi> hath inſtamped his image of ſoueraigntie in <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Caeſars,</hi> ſet the Crowne vpon their heads, put the ſcepter into their hands, and created them chiefe Monarches, in their territories and dominions, ouer all others, next vnder himſelfe. And from and by them (through the like impreſsion made) God deriues vnto other Prime perſons vnder them, their eminent di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnitie, in places of lawfull authoritie. So that Vice-Royes, and all others, in their ſeuerall rankes of gouernment, do beare the ſtampe and impreſsion of God, and the King, more or leſſe, accordingly anſwerable to their diſtinct and ſeuerall orders and degrees.</p>
            <p>Moreouer; the better to eſtabliſh and ratifie this wholſome ordinance, in this excellent eutaxie, and to grace and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard the perſons of theſe Delegates, as ſacred and inviolable, in their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsiue authoritie. God honoureth them with his owne ſtile and title of <hi>Gods;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82. <hi>v.</hi> 1.6. <hi>v.</hi> 7.</note> not as if they were ſuch of their owne nature and being (for ſo they are but
<pb facs="tcp:3592:4"/>men, and <hi>die</hi> they muſt like men, and remaine accountant to him, the great God, for their dealings towards the meanest man) but through his grace communicating thus farre his regencie vnto them. And ſo they are as Gods among men (as bearing Gods image in their power ouer men) and <hi>Gods vnto men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hom, homini Deus. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> as a <hi>common good</hi> of Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiding (in faithfull diſpenſation of their function) for the good of men.</p>
            <p>Yet further; as Magiſtrates are Gods creation, and ordination, in regard of their function; ſo are they dependant on God, for abilitie to the execution of their function, which they receiue from his effectuall diſpenſation &amp; prouidence. <hi>Counſell is mine</hi> (ſaith wiſdome) <hi>and ſound wiſdom:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 8.14.</note> 
               <hi>I am vnderſtanding, I haue ſtrength.</hi> Mortall men must in no wiſe glory in any their owne ſtrength or wiſdome, with the proud King of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> leſt it proue coſtly to them as it did vnto him.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai.</hi> 10.12, 13.</note> From Gods gracious gift they receiue their annoynting, <hi>other hearts</hi> with <hi>Saul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.9.</note> 
               <hi>vnderſtanding
<pb facs="tcp:3592:4"/>hearts</hi> with <hi>Solomon to iudge the people.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 3.9, 12.</note> And thus inveſted with theſe ſingular endowments, as with princely <hi>diademes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 29.14.</note> and richly furniſhed with thoſe heroicall virtues, of wiſdom, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, fortitude, and feare of the Lord, they grow vndaunted for courage, and conſtant for reſolution, in vndertaking &amp; vndergoing of weighty imployments; faithfull in diſpatch of worthy ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; vnweariable for indeuour in ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy performances; and invincible for patience, in induring oppoſitions, and clamors, of all thoſe ſons of Belial, who <hi>deſpiſe dominion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jude v.</hi> 8. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.10.</note> 
               <hi>ſpeake euill of dignities,</hi> or will not yeeld obedience to wholſome lawes, nor ſubmit their necks to needfull diſcipline.</p>
            <p>Finally; that all may be well, and all, ſay we, is well that ends well. The good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the end doth highly commend the goodneſſe of the act. Now the end of all acts in Magiſtracy (aſwell as in Miniſterie) muſt be ſquared by that the <hi>Apoſtles Canon, let all things be done vnto edifying:</hi> and nothing muſt
<pb facs="tcp:3592:5"/>be done idly or vnprofitably,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Baſil.</note> tending to no good end and purpoſe. Gouernors muſt therefore in all their acts and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, ayme at the right end and ſcope of gouernment, the glory of God in the good of men. Which end ſhall be most happily atchieued, if they ſhall princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally eye and reſpect both the Tables of Gods law, whereof they are the Great-Lords Keepers. Religion or piety to God, in the first Table, the baſis and foundation of a truly-proſperous politie: And equitie and iuſtice to man, in the ſecond, the nerues and ſinewes of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ſociety. Thus when Magiſtrates ayme at theſe ends in gouernment; that religion be entertained, the Goſpell coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced, and piety promoted; and, that innocencie be defended, right preſerued, and vice puniſhed; and, that all be righted, none wronged. Then ſhall Church and Common-weale ioyntly and mutually liue and loue, grow proſperous and renowmed, and God ſhall haue glory from the well-orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red communities of men, and men
<pb facs="tcp:3592:5"/>felicitie in bleſſed communion with God.</p>
            <p>Now all proſperous ſucceſſe, in vſe of best meanes for atchieuing theſe ends, muſt be expected and fetched from the bleſsing of God,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Joh:</hi> 3.27.</note> 
               <hi>without whom no mortall man can euer proue happy.</hi> For <hi>a man can receiue nothing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it be giuen him from heauen:</hi> No counſells of man proue healthfull and ſucceſsfull, vnleſſe God aſsist, and giue a bleſsing. Which meditation is the argument of that heauenly hymne, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piled by <hi>Dauid</hi> for his ſon <hi>Salomons</hi> vſe, or by <hi>Salomon</hi> himſelf,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal:</hi> 127.</note> inſtructed of God with deep wiſdom-politicall, for his owne:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>Except the Lord build the houſe, they labour in vaine that build it; except the Lord keep the Citie, the watchman waketh but in vaine. It is in vaine for you to riſe vp early, to ſit vp late, to eat the bread of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes; for ſo he giueth his beloued ſleepe.</hi> The building of the houſe, the watching of the Citie, early vp-riſing, and late downe-ſitting, aſsiduous labour,
<pb facs="tcp:3592:6"/>and carking care are all in vaine, vnles God aſsist and giue a bleſsing. And ſo doth <hi>Gregory Nazianzene</hi> moſt ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantly paranomaze the ſumme and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of that diuine Pſalme.
<q>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
               </q>
which memorable Diſtick I thus, in homely Engliſh, expreſſe.</p>
            <q>
               <l>If God giue good ſucceſſe, enuie can not preuaile.</l>
               <l>If God denie ſucceſſe, labour can naught auaile.</l>
            </q>
            <p>If God from heauen ſhall bleſſe and proſper, what force or fraud below can croſſe or controll? But, if God from heauen ſhall croſſe and curſe, what power or wit of man ſhall not proue vaine and fruſtrate? The fencing of Kingdomes, and ſafe-guarding of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries with wholſome lawes and politicall conſtitutions, with Armies and Nauies, with trenches &amp; bulwarks, with leagues and alliances; yea, with infinite heapes
<pb facs="tcp:3592:6"/>of gold and ſiluer (which <hi>Dionyſius</hi> eſteemed <hi>the adamantine bonds of Empires</hi>) is all in vaine,<note place="margin">Adamantina vincula imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum.</note> vnleſſe God aſsist and giue a bleſsing. Moſt deliberate counſels and beſt deſigned attempts faile of good ſucceſſe, for want of Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing; to rebuke the pride of mans pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming weakneſſe. And weaker meanes vſed, in want of ſtronger, through di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine aſsiſtance, work wonderfull effects; to correct mans diffidence, and to worke dependance on God: according to thoſe precepts and promiſes.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37. <hi>v.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>Truſt in the Lord and doe good: ſo ſhalt thou dwell in the land, and verily thou ſhalt be fed.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>Delight thy ſelfe alſo in the Lord, and he ſhall giue thee the deſires of thine heart. Commit thy way vnto the Lord;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>truſt alſo in him, and he ſhall bring it to paſſe.</hi> And according to that moſt memorable practiſe: we know not what to doe, but our eyes are vpon thee.</p>
            <p>And that the flouriſhing ſtate of Common-wealths ſprings out rather from the bleſsing of Gods diuine proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,
<pb facs="tcp:3592:7"/>then from the beſt fore-cast of humane prudence, <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> the witnes of times, and light of truth, doth plainly teſtifie. To which alſo <hi>Heathens</hi> doe giue their ſuffrages from the dim ſight of humane obſeruation.<note place="margin">Vbi non Deus ſed mortalis ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis prae ſt, ibi malorum nullu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> est effugium. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>4.</hi> Dei ope &amp; aux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ilio multò magis R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mpubl. Rema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam quam ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione hominum &amp; conſilio gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernari. Cic. pro Rabitio.</note> For ſo <hi>Plato</hi> profeſſeth of Common-weales in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon: <hi>Where not God but ſome mortall man is preſident, there's no auoydall of any euill.</hi> And <hi>Cicero</hi> of the Romane ſtate in ſpeciall: <hi>The Romane ſtate was proſperouſly go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned much rather by the aide and helpe of God, than by mans reaſon and counſell humane.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in a word, that nothing can be well done, and happily ſucceede in Citie or familie, Church or Common-wealth, without the good will and good worke of God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.11.</note> 
               <hi>who worketh all things after the counſell of his own will, S. Paul</hi> doth intimate, when he earneſtly <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts, That firſt of all ſupplications,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>prayers, interceſſions, and giuing of thanks be made for all</hi> conditions of <hi>men: for Kings and for all that are
<pb facs="tcp:3592:7"/>in authoritie, that,</hi> through Gods good bleſsing on their good indeuours, <hi>we</hi> their ſubiects, in our inferior condition, <hi>may lead a quiet and a peaceable life in all godlineſſe and honeſtie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſumme of all, in ſhort, is this: <hi>Kings</hi> as <hi>ſupreme,</hi> and other <hi>gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors</hi> as ſent by God and them,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13, 14.</note> doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue their high places, and princely gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, their function and execution, voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and diſpenſation, authoritie and abilitie, and all happy ſucceſſe and good fruit in gouernment, for the weale and welfare of themſelues and theirs, from that all-wiſe and all-ruling <hi>Monarch,</hi> great <hi>Counſellor,</hi> and <hi>Law-giuer,</hi> the eſſentiall wiſdome, the ſon of God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſal.</hi> 9.6. <hi>Jam:</hi> 4.12.</note> who (with the Father, and Holy Spirit, one true God) is the <hi>bleſſed and onely Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentate, the King of Kings and Lord of Lords,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 6.15.</note> 
               <hi>the King eternall, immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, inviſible, and only wiſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.17.</note> 
               <hi>to whom</hi> from them all in all their deſignes is to <hi>be</hi> giuen, as the maine end of their go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, <hi>all honor and glory for euer and euer. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3592:8"/>
Now, Right Honorable Lord, and Reuerend Sages, moſt wiſe and worthy interpreters of Law, and Diſpenſers of Iuſtice, great Guardians, vnder God and King, of Church and Common-wealth, as I freely acknowledge to the glory of God and honour of the King (for which I bleſſe God on the knees of my heart) that God hath bleſſed this Land with many true Worthies, on Benches in Courts of equitie and iuſtice (bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhining ſtars, reſtleſſe in motion, in their orbe of gouernment:) ſo I moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beſeech you to giue leaue to me, your ſeruant in the Lord, (without your cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure) from ſincere affection, and duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full reſpect to your perſons, to put you in minde of that which you know right well (being ſo well furniſhed with wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome humane and diuine) and I am well aſſured (on my ſmall obſeruation, and ſhort experience) you endenour to practiſe (through the ſpirit of grace in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiring and inabling you) for diſcharge of that truſt repoſed in you in your pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like imployments, in this body politique,
<pb facs="tcp:3592:8"/>by our gracious <hi>GOD,</hi> and our religious <hi>KING.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The thing is this.</p>
            <p>Sith the God of heauen and earth is the first mouer, in his ſupreme orbe of gouernment, all you his ſecondarie mouers, in this your orbe of gouernment, in this heauen of our politie, ought to moue after the will and ordination of God, and not (as in that other Heauen) by any rapt motion from your priuate affection, nor yet irregular from inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate paſsion, nor by that of trepidation for feare of mortall man. You must in your motion run the ſame courſe, or vſe the ſame end with God himſelfe; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the glory of God, in our good of Church and Common-wealth, which, as the lower earth, are preſerued and che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed, with heauenly influence, through your well-ordered and well-ordering motion. And ſuch ſubordination will ſurely cauſe an heauenly harmony, and heart-pleaſing conſent, in a circular re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolution thus.</p>
            <p>God is the ordeyner of our King,
<pb facs="tcp:3592:9"/>the King the image of God, the Law the worke of the King, Iudges interpreters of our Law, Magiſtrates with them di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſers, Iuſtice our fruit of Law di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſed, this fruit of iuſtice the good of the people, the good of the people the honour of our King, this honour of our King, the glory of God, the ordeiner, orderer, and bleſſer of all. And ſo in this regular and circular revolution, all mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion begins in God, and ends in God, for mans felicitie, and Gods glory, infinitely, and eternally.</p>
            <p>Great, you ſee, is your honour: as great is your charge. A double charge; from God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. <hi>v.</hi> 18, 19, 20.</note> from King. God <hi>chargeth</hi> the King: God and King (whoſe <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters</hi> and <hi>ſword-bearers</hi> you are) haue charged you.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.4.</note> Your office then of Magiſtracie (as ours of Miniſtery) is not ſo much <hi>nomen honoris</hi> as <hi>oneris.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug: de Ciuit. Dei l. <hi>19.</hi> c. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> Your deſire must therefore be, not ſo much <hi>praeeſſe,</hi> as <hi>prodeſſe,</hi> to beare rule as to profit,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Luc:</hi> 21.25.</note> to be <hi>benefactors,</hi> for the good of men; that is your end, who are publique Patrons, &amp; oracles of your
<pb facs="tcp:3592:9"/>Country, Hauens, and Refuges to poore diſtreſſed ones. Your ſymbole must be that of <hi>Alphonſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Alphonſ. Nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politan. Rex.</note> The <hi>Pelican</hi> with her own bill picking and drawing bloud out of her owne breaſt, with this inſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, <hi>Pro lege &amp; pro grege:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Magiſtra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us virio oſtendit. Ariſt. ex Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ante.</note> Herein <hi>will Magiſtracie ſhew your man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, where as theſe matters of iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are diſpoſed and diſpenſed not by your ſelues alone, but by many other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior organs and inſtruments, who need due inſpection and daily information;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Hom. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> as interpreters of Law inſtruct them; as Moderators of Iuſtice direct them; as charged your ſelues of God and King to doe iuſtice, lay great charge on them; yea, as armed with power coactiue, by vertue thereof (as far as ſhall be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and needfull) as Guardians of equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, vrge them to doe, what God and King, law and conſcience, equitie and honeſtie exact at their hands; that this <hi>chaſte Virgin Iuſtice</hi> be not by them deſlowred,<note place="margin">Heſiod.</note> 
               <hi>that conſcience of crime</hi> (in vnrighteous dealing) <hi>may not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly<note place="margin">Hieron. epist.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3592:10"/>wound their conſciences at home, nor their name and familie outwardly beſmeared with iuſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch and ignominie abroad:</hi> But that good right be maintained, good conſcience diſcharged, good name preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; that God may be honoured,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Gods people benefited, the Common-wealth cheriſhed, the Church inlarged, our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God and ſociety with men may become most comfortable, happy, and bleſſed, while iudgment and iuſtice are equally diſpenſed of all manner per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons vnder God and King, as from God, by God, and for God; as is more largely declared in this inſuing Treatiſe; which, being heretofore once vttered by me, and now drawne into publique by effectuall perſwaſion of others, I now make bold to preſent to your Honours, and Worſhips, becauſe it concernes you all, though for manner not ſo worthy (as I well could wiſh) your learned wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes view and approbation. Well ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, that, in your priuacie and retired<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe from your weighty imployments,
<pb facs="tcp:3592:10"/>you will pleaſe to peruſe it, couering what faults and ſlips you eſpie therein, with your robes of loue, and Christian <hi>Charitie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 4.8.</note> not looking at my want of diſcharge of my dutie (which I ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly acknowledge, and ſue for pardon thereof at the hands of God and you) but at the better diſcharge of your owne (whereto this my poore labour, as a weake meane, would further): For ſo you ſtand charged of God, and the King: <hi>Take heede</hi> therefore <hi>what yee doe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron:</hi> 19.6.</note> 
               <hi>for yee iudge not for man but for the Lord.</hi> And the Lord be with you in the iudgment. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honors, and Worſhips, in all dutie, to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded,</hi> William Pemberton.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:3592:11"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3592:11"/>
            <head>The Charge of GOD and the KING.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>DEVTER. 1.16, 17.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="16">
                     <hi>16.</hi> And I charged your Iudges at that time ſaying: Heare the <hi>cauſes</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene your brethren, and iudge righteouſly betweene euery man and his brother, and the ſtranger that is with him.</p>
                  <p n="17">
                     <hi>17.</hi> Yee ſhall not reſpect perſons in iudgment, <hi>but</hi> you ſhall heare the ſmall aſwell as the great: you ſhall not be afraid of the face of man, for the iudgment is Gods: and the cauſe that is too hard for you, bring it vnto me, and I will heare it.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>L the counſels and works of God (the moſt mighty Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, &amp; moſt wiſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſer of all things) doe proceede from the <hi>good pleaſure</hi> of Gods will,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1 12.</note> which
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3592:12"/>is the cauſe of all cauſes; and tend to the <hi>glory</hi> of his name,<note place="margin">Voluntas Dei omnium quae ſunt ipſa eſt cauſa. Aug: de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en: contra Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nich: l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi> Prou: <hi>16.14.</hi>
               </note> which is the end of all ends. And that in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation of his mercy, in the graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſaluation and happines of ſome; and of his iuſtice, in the deſerued condemnation and miſery of others. And this our naturall and temporary life, which we liue on earth, is, in the counſell and decree of God, a praepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and degree to a better life. And in the elect, to omit the reſt, to a life ſpirituall and ſupernaturall, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun on earth in this time of grace, and continued in Heauen, in that eternitie of glory. This life well led, in faith and obedience, doth highly aduance vs to felicitie and happines: This life ill led, in infidelitie and ſin, doth deeply depreſſe vs into miſerie and wretchedneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The entrance of Lawes.</note>Now that man on earth might liue well, God did giue him a <hi>Rule</hi> to liue by. This <hi>Rule</hi> is the <hi>Law</hi> of God (the rule of piety, the ſquare of equitie) firſt inſtamped in mans nature in his
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3592:12"/>created innocencie.<note place="margin">Antequa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pta fuit in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum legthus, in mentibus vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gebat. Ambr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> lib. <hi>4.</hi> de Abra: hamo Patriare! cap. <hi>4.</hi> Eph <hi>4.24.</hi> In libro aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Iudae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</note> For what was that <hi>Image</hi> of God in man conſiſting of <hi>righteouſneſſe, holineſſe,</hi> and <hi>trueth,</hi> but <hi>Lex primordialis, a primordiall Law,</hi> (as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſpeakes) exactly requiring and abſolutely inabling the performance of duties of piety to God, and of equitie to man, both in habite and act; and that in ſinceritie and perfection of them both? And what was the <hi>Morall Law</hi> proclaimed on <hi>Mount Sinah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.</note> after that man had defaced Gods image, by tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his command, but this <hi>primor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diall Law</hi> renewed and repeated, as an abſolute and eternall rule and ſquare, of piety to God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 31.18.</note> and equitie to man, which <hi>God</hi> with his owne <hi>fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> did <hi>ingraue in two Tables of ſtone,</hi> and gaue vnto <hi>Moſes</hi> for the vſe of his Church?</p>
            <p>This <hi>Morall Law</hi> requires obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, according to the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or exact perfection thereof, but it giues no abilitie to performe obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. It ſheweth what man <hi>now</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:3592:13"/>ought to doe, what <hi>once</hi> he could haue done; but not what he <hi>now</hi> can do, nor what <hi>it</hi> will inable him to do; but accuſeth and accurſeth euery man, as guilty of ſinne, for the leaſt tranſgreſſion of it. Whereupon God in mercy, to releeue mans miſery, to this law of works giuen in <hi>Sinah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.</note> did adde another <hi>Law,</hi> (as the Apoſtle ſtiles it) the <hi>Law of Faith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.27. <hi>Iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 2.3. <hi>Mich.</hi> 4.2.</note> giuen in <hi>Sion,</hi> which promiſeth life and bleſſedneſſe to all that beleeue in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The <hi>law of workes,</hi> called the <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall law,</hi> is grounded on <hi>nature,</hi> and may be called <hi>Lex timoris, the law of feare;</hi> becauſe, through our impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tencie, it doth terrifie and affright vs.</p>
            <p>The <hi>law of Faith</hi> (which is the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell</hi>) is grounded on <hi>Gods grace,</hi> and may be called <hi>Lex amoris,</hi> the <hi>law of Loue;</hi> for <hi>God ſo loued</hi> vs,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>:</hi> 3.16.</note> 
               <hi>that he gaue his Sonne</hi> for vs; and it effectually worketh the loue of God in vs, and reftoreth vs againe to bleſſedneſſe with God.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:3592:13"/>
Man doth againe recouer this bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſednes with God, while he is driuen from himſelfe and his ſinnes, by the fearefull threats of the law <hi>morall,</hi> and is allured vnto <hi>Chriſt</hi> by the ſweet promiſes of the <hi>Goſpell, this law of Faith;</hi> and is daily renewed by the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of grace vnto conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to the law of works, which ſtill remaineth, as a <hi>Rule</hi> of good life (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring obedience of faith,<note place="margin">Aug: lib. <hi>3.</hi> ad Bonifacium c. <hi>4.</hi> &amp; contra Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum Manich.</note> in way of thankfulnes) till <hi>Gods</hi> glorious <hi>image</hi> be againe repaired in vs, and that eternitie of <hi>glory<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> be conferred vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs.</p>
            <p>In the meane time, for the ſpace of this life, many diſorders and miſde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanors remaine ſtill in the world. For the greater part of men will not be reformed: the better part are but in part ſanctified. Theſe ſin of weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, thoſe of wilfulneſſe: both haue neede of all good helps, for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation to good, or reſtraint from euill.</p>
            <p>Wherevpon God hath in wiſdom
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3592:14"/>ordeined <hi>Humane Lawes,</hi> and hath appointed <hi>Kings,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cuſtedes &amp; vind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ces vtriuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Tabulae D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut: <hi>17.</hi> Eſa. <hi>49.23.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Princes,</hi> and <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates</hi> to be <hi>keepers of both the Tables of the Morall Law: Nurſing-fathers and Nurſing-mothers vnto his</hi> militant <hi>Church,</hi> and conſtant <hi>Defenders</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Faith.</p>
            <p>And all their <hi>good</hi> Lawes both <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiasticall</hi> and <hi>Ciuill</hi> are backs and props vnto Gods holy Law, and, in their due and faithfull execution, effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall meanes to procure the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation thereof. And, in a word, of all good Lawes, whether <hi>written</hi> or <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written</hi> there is a twofold end or ſcope, as namely, they do reſpect and ayme at, either piety and godlineſſe from man to God, that a bleſſed communion may be maintained be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene man and God; or equitie &amp; iuſtice from man to man, that a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable communion and ſweet ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie may be preſerued betweene man and man.</p>
            <p>And ſurely, theſe humane lawes, of <hi>Kings</hi> &amp; <hi>Rulers,</hi> being wiſely enacted<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:3592:14"/>and duely executed, by <hi>Iudges</hi> and <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> competent, and faithfull in the execution of their function, are ſoueraigne helps for the cure of vice, by inflicting puniſhment on malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors; and to allure to virtue by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring rewards, and defending of well-doers; and to right euery man in his righteous cauſe, that euery man may enioy his own; That ſo <hi>we may lead a quiet and a peaceable life,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.2.</note> 
               <hi>in all godlineſſe and honeſtie.</hi> And to this purpoſe are we to <hi>pray</hi> to God for them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 1.</note> and for this end are they <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned</hi> to this function by God;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1, 4</note> and for the better diſcharge of their office and dutie, they receiue a <hi>charge</hi> from <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo to deſcend to our preſent purpoſe, and to apply my ſelf wholy to time and occaſion; theſe words, of this Scripture, doe commend to our view, a <hi>ſpeciall Charge giuen by</hi> GOD <hi>and the</hi> KING <hi>to Iudges and Magiſtrates for execution of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:3592:15"/>
This <hi>Charge</hi> (I ſay) firſt is giuen of <hi>God;</hi> for <hi>Moſes</hi> was an holy <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and ſpake nothing but from the mouth of God, or by inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the <hi>Spirit</hi> of God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this is the <hi>Charge of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">Act: <hi>7.35.</hi> Bertram de po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia Iudaica cap. <hi>5.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>utr.</note> I call it the <hi>Charge of the King;</hi> for <hi>Moſes</hi> was <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>chiefe Ruler of Gods people:</hi> his autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie was <hi>Regall,</hi> his power <hi>Soueraigne,</hi> not differing in <hi>nature,</hi> but in name, from that of a <hi>King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this <hi>Charge</hi> we may conſider, 1. The giuing of the Charge: <hi>And I charged your Iudges at that time, ſaying.</hi> 2. The Charge giuen: <hi>Heare the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes betweene your brethren &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> In the <hi>giuing</hi> of the Charge, we may obſerue, 1. The perſon that gaue it, Moſes, <hi>I charged.</hi> 2. The perſons to whom it was giuen, the Iudges, <hi>your Iudges.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>thing</hi> giuen, for nature, a Charge. <hi>I charged.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The <hi>time</hi> when it was giuen, <hi>at that time,</hi> namely of their election,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3592:15"/>and deſignation to their function: <hi>And I charged your Iudges at that time, ſaying.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> In the Charge <hi>giuen</hi> we may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue, 1. <hi>Inſtructions or iniunctions</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the Iudges, which are two. Firſt, to heare cauſes deliberately, <hi>Heare the cauſes.</hi> Secondly, to iudge righteouſly, <hi>and iudge righteouſly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>parties</hi> betweene whom they muſt heare and iudge, propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, firſt, in relation to the Iudges, <hi>your brethren:</hi> ſecondly, in relation among themſelues, <hi>betweene euery man and his brother,</hi> that is, of the ſame <hi>Nation,</hi> of the ſame <hi>Religion:</hi> neither only ſo, but (as the meaning is more plainly opened) <hi>betweene euery man and the ſtranger that is with him.</hi> A <hi>ſtranger,</hi> for kindred, <hi>Nation,</hi> or <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> is yet a brother for <hi>common</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and <hi>humane</hi> condition, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt haue right done to him as being <hi>a brother.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Admonitions or cautions</hi> againſt peſtilent impediments, which are fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3592:16"/>enemies to equitie and iuſtice; and they are two.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Acceptation</hi> of perſons, on ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter reſpects: <hi>Yee ſhall not reſpect perſons in iudgment, but you ſhall heare the ſmall aſwell as the great.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Feare</hi> of mens <hi>greatneſſe</hi> who will be offended at iuſtice: <hi>You ſhall not be afraid of the face of man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Reaſons</hi> to inforce the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of the <hi>iniunctions,</hi> and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of the <hi>cautions:</hi> 1. <hi>for the iudgement is Gods.</hi> 2. <hi>The charge is from God,</hi> as in the firſt words, <hi>I char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</hi> As if he ſhould haue ſaid; God hath charged you to do right; God will maintaine you in doing right; therefore heare deliberately, iudge righteouſly, accept no mans perſon, feare no mans face, but do right to the ſmall as well as the great; to the ſtranger as well as the brother.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>A caſe of reſeruation</hi> of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in cauſes too difficult, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultation or appeale to the chiefeſt Iudge: <hi>And the cauſe that is too hard
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3592:16"/>for you bring vnto mee, and I will heare it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this I take to be the intent and ſubſtance of this Charge of God and the King, giuen by Moſes dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly to the Iudges of Iſrael, but in them to all other Iudges and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates; yea all other officers, all miniſters and inſtruments of iuſtice (for the hand of Iuſtice hath many fingers) as Counſellors, Pleaders, Aduocates, Sollicitors, Shiriffes, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, witneſſes, and the reſt. And it doth meerely concerne, both <hi>God</hi> and <hi>King, Church</hi> and <hi>Common-weale,</hi> and euery ſtate and perſon in them both, and affords fit matter for this preſent occaſion, and profitable dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction for all ſuch purpoſes. In ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king whereof, that I may ſay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of euery thing, I muſt be ſhort in all. And in all and euery thing, I do moſt humbly craue, Gods power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>direction,</hi> that I may be able to ſpeake; your fauourable <hi>attention,</hi> that I may be heard; and <hi>Gods</hi> gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3592:17"/>
               <hi>bleſsing</hi> vpon that which ſhall be ſpoken and heard, that it may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound to <hi>Gods</hi> glory, and to <hi>our</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and comfort, and ſo I proceede.</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>Firſt generall Part. Giuing of the charge.</head>
               <p>The <hi>first</hi> generall part formerly propounded, is the giuing of the charge: <hi>And I charged your Iudges at that time ſaying.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>I. Point.</hi> The Perſons who gaue the Charge.</note> And the firſt parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular therein obſerued, was the <hi>perſon</hi> who gaue it, <hi>I,</hi> that is, <hi>Moſes.</hi> This one perſon <hi>Moſes</hi> ſuſtaines a double perſon:<note place="margin">1. God.</note> Firſt of <hi>God,</hi> as he was a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet of God, and ſpake from the mouth of God.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2. The King.</hi> Prudentiſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mus L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>giſlator, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſſimus Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceps, ac Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta maximus. Philo in vita Moſis.</note> Secondly, of a <hi>King,</hi> as he was the <hi>chiefe Ruler</hi> and gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; and ſo it is the <hi>charge of</hi> GOD <hi>and the</hi> KING.</p>
               <p>Firſt this was the <hi>Charge of God;</hi> for <hi>Moſes</hi> the man of God, was (as was ſaid) an holy <hi>Prophet</hi> of God, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly called of God, to this holy function; immediately aſſiſted and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3592:17"/>directed in his execution by God: and what he injoyned to this people, he receiued it from God; from Gods <hi>mouth,</hi> or by <hi>inſpiration</hi> of his Spirit, or by ſome ſuch ſpeciall and <hi>infallible</hi> information of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> elected Iudges to helpe and aſſiſt him in iudging of cauſes (with varietie and multitude whereof hee was ouer-charged) and this he did by the wiſe and godly counſell of his father in law <hi>Iethro,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.</note> yet vpon conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation alſo firſt had with God, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe anſwer from the heauenly <hi>Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle.</hi> For ſo <hi>Iethro</hi> aduiſed him <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.23. <hi>If thou ſhalt doe this thing</hi> (that is, elect ſome aſſiſtant Iudges) <hi>and God command thee ſo, then ſhalt thou be able to endure.</hi> And the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of <hi>Moſes</hi> conſulting with God did giue teſtimonie to this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſement of <hi>Iethro</hi> as the counſell of God: and therefore this election of Iudges by <hi>Moſes</hi> was in deede and effect, the election of God; and this <hi>Charge</hi> giuen to theſe New-elect, was accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3592:18"/>the charge of God. Whence it followeth as a ground of all that I haue to ſpeake, that</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The charge for right execution of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice giuen to Iudges by the Prophets of God is to be accounted the charge of God.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Doctr.</note> This charge God giueth ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times immediately with his owne mouth:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 10.</note> thus God proclaimed the <hi>Morall</hi> Law, which conteines all the grounds of equitie and iuſtice, by his immediate voice; and deliuered to <hi>Moſes</hi> not onely the <hi>Ceremonials,</hi> but alſo <hi>Iudicials</hi> by his immediate dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: and by <hi>Moſes</hi> vnto the Church, as <hi>Leuit.</hi> 19.35. <hi>Yee ſhall not doe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe in iudgement, in line, in weight, or in meaſure.</hi> And <hi>Moſes</hi> in the execution of his weighty functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, did conſult with God, in his heauenly Oracle; as did alſo <hi>Dauid,</hi> and others,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.7, 8.</note> in caſes of difficultie, not expreſſed in Gods word. And God directed <hi>Ioſhua,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Joſh.</hi> 1.1, 2.</note> after the death of <hi>Moſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>God giues this Charge ſometimes
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3592:18"/>by his inſtruments, as <hi>Prophets, Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,</hi> and <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the <hi>Goſpell:</hi> By <hi>Prophets,</hi> as by <hi>Moſes</hi> to theſe Iudges in this place; and ſo by <hi>Iſaiah</hi> to the <hi>Iudges of Iudah,</hi> Iſ. 1.17. <hi>Seeke iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, releeue the oppreſſed, iudge the fatherleſſe, plead for the widow.</hi> By the prophet <hi>Ieremiah</hi> to the King of Iudah and his ſeruants, Ierem. 2.2, 3. <hi>Execute yee iudgement and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and deliuer the ſpoiled out of the hand of the oppreſſor: and do no wrong, doe no violence to the ſtranger, the fatherleſſe, nor the widow, neither ſhed innocent blood in this place.</hi> And Chap. 21. v. 12. <hi>O houſe of Dauid, thus ſaith the Lord, execute iudgement in the morning, and deliuer him that is ſpoiled out of the hand of the oppreſſor.</hi> By the kingly prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> Pſal. 2.10. <hi>Be wiſe now therefore, ô yee Kings: be inſtructed yee Iudges of the earth.</hi> By the prophet <hi>Zachary</hi> to the Iewes, <hi>Thus ſpeaketh the Lord of Hoſtes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zach.</hi> 7.9.</note> 
                  <hi>exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute iudgement, ſhew mercy.</hi> And againe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zach.</hi> 8.16.</note> 
                  <hi>Execute the iudgement of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3592:19"/>trueth and peace in your gates.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By his holy <hi>Apoſtles</hi> vnto <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Magiſtrates, as the Apoſtle <hi>S. Paul</hi> (one for all the reſt) ſets downe the office and charge of a Iudge or Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.3, 4. ſaying, <hi>Rulers are not a terrour to good workes but to the euill:</hi> againe, <hi>The Ruler is the miniſter of God, a reuenger to execute wrath vpon him that doth euill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, God giues this charge by the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> who are his <hi>Ambaſſadors</hi> in matters of God, to declare his will to the people of God. And we (Gods miniſters) ſtand <hi>charged</hi> of God (as <hi>Timothie</hi> of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>before God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.21.</note> 
                  <hi>and the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and the elect Angels,</hi> that we <hi>obſerue all that</hi> God injoynes vs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>preiudice,</hi> and we muſt do <hi>nothing of partialitie,</hi> but muſt <hi>diuide the word of God aright,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2: 15.</note> diſpenſing Gods <hi>myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> as his faithfull <hi>ſtewards,</hi> and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to our <hi>Lords familie, to each one his due portion,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 12.42.</note> 
                  <hi>in due ſeaſon:</hi> and ſo preſcribing to Iudges and Rulers
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3592:19"/>their duties from God, as we our ſelues expect to be iudged of God; and we muſt not dare to <hi>corrupt the word of God; but as of ſinceritie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.17.</note> 
                  <hi>as of God, in the ſight of God, ſo ought we to ſpeake in Chriſt:</hi> and ſo I deſire to ſpeake vnto you.</p>
               <p>Wherefore, right Honorable and beloued in the Lord,<note place="margin">Vſe.</note> let mee intreat you from the Lord, that <hi>you receiue from vs, who ſerue God in this fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, our charge for iuſtice as the charge of God;</hi> not meaſuring the weight of our embaſſage by the meanneſſe of our perſons, but weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the worthineſſe of our calling, and giuing entertainment to the truth, which we ſpeake according to Gods word, <hi>not as the word of man, but of God;</hi> alwaies remembring that of our Sauiour to his Diſciples, and in them to vs; <hi>Behold, I ſend you.</hi> and, <hi>He that heareth you heareth me;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc:</hi> 10. <hi>v.</hi> 3, 16</note> 
                  <hi>and he that deſpiſeth you deſpiſeth me.</hi> And that worthy ſaying of our moſt <hi>learned</hi> &amp; <hi>religious King</hi> in a ſolemne
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3592:20"/>diſputation in the <hi>Vniuerſitie. The King himſelfe ought to obey the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">At Cambridge March <hi>16 14.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>tanquam ſpirituali medico ex ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo Dei praeſcribenti, as to a ſpirituall Phyſician preſcribing to him out of the word of God.</hi> And this accords with his <hi>Maieſties</hi> inſtructions to the <hi>Prince</hi> his eldeſt ſonne;<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>pag.</hi> 10.</note> 
                  <hi>When any of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall office-bearers in the Church ſpeaketh vnto you any thing that is well warranted by the word, reuerence and obey them as the Heraulds of the most high God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo much of this, as the <hi>Charge of God:</hi> Now I come to it as the <hi>Charge of the King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">2. The King giues this Charge.</note>The ſecond perſon whom <hi>Moſes</hi> ſuſteineth in giuing of this Charge is the perſon of the <hi>King;</hi> for hee was deſigned <hi>chiefe Ruler</hi> and <hi>Iudge</hi> of Gods people: his authoritie was <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall,</hi> his power <hi>Soueraigne,</hi> though he gouerned alſo by others as aſſiſtants and counſellors.</p>
               <p>Whence <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>chiefe Rulers</hi> may take patterne for their practiſe,<note place="margin">Doctr.</note>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:3592:20"/>
                  <hi>to giue ſpeciall Charge to their Delegates and Deputies, to execute iuſt iudgement vnto the people.</hi> For ſo <hi>Moſes</hi> the chiefe Ruler gaue charge to theſe new-elected Iudges and Rulers to heare and indge righteouſly the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of all men. Such a charge, for a farewell, did holy <hi>King Dauid</hi> giue vnto <hi>Salomon</hi> his ſucceeding ſonne, 1. King. 2.2, 3. <hi>I goe the way of all the earth: be thou ſtrong therefore, and ſhew thy ſelfe a man. And take heede to the charge of the Lord thy God to walke in his wayes, and to keepe his ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes</hi> &amp;c. When he further injoynes him, according to his wiſdom to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute iuſtice on <hi>Ioab</hi> and <hi>Shimei,</hi> and to ſhew mercy and kindnes to the ſons of <hi>Barzillai.</hi> The <hi>Aegyptian Kings</hi> were wont (as <hi>Plutarch</hi> reporteth) by the cuſtome of their country, to giue an oath to ſuch as were appointed their Iudges, that they ſhould not ſpeake or doe vnrighteouſly in iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, though the King himſelfe ſhould charge and command them.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:3592:21"/>Which commendable practiſe <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iane</hi> the Emperor did worthily imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, and gaue a drawne ſword to the <hi>Pretorian Lieutenant</hi> before all his Nobles, ſaying vnto him: <hi>Si bonus fuero pro me vtitor</hi> (hoc gladio) <hi>ſin malus contrame. If I ſhall be good vſe this ſword for me, if euill, againſt me.</hi> or thus: <hi>Hoc gladio pro me vtar is, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nec iuſta fecero: ſi iniuſta ſecero, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra me vtaris. As long as I ſhall doe thoſe things which are iuſt, vſe this ſword for me: if I do things vniust, vſe it against me.</hi> A fact and ſpeach moſt worthy an <hi>Emperor!</hi> whoſe example, at leaſt in the ſcope thereof, is fit to be imitated of euery good King; who ought to acknowledge, that God hath aduanced him, as a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle <hi>God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l. 82.</note> to ſit on the Throne, and to rule ouer all others for the common good of all. The oath which the King adminiſtreth to Iudges, binds them to ſtrict obſeruation of iuſtice, as it is recorded in the ſtature of the 18. of <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>III.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:3592:21"/>
                  <q>Ye ſhall do euen law &amp; execution of right to all his ſubiects rich and poore,<note place="margin">The oath of Iudges 18. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3 printed <hi>anno D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>mius</hi> 1578. <hi>p</hi> 106.</note> without hauing regard of any perſon. And that yee denie to no man common right, by the Kings letters, nor none other mans, nor for none other cauſe, and in caſe any letters come come to you contrary to the law, that yee do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by ſuch letters, but certifie the King thereof, and goe forth to doe the law, notwithſtanding the ſame letters.</q> And this is agreable to the commandement of <hi>Antiochus</hi> the King of <hi>Aſia;</hi> 
                  <q>That if letters came from him, or his Nobles to interrupt the courſe of iuſtice, they ſhould pocket them vp, ſuppoſing them to be vnwittingly written, and ſo to proceed in a ſtrict courſe of iuſtice.</q>
               </p>
               <p>A good King giues ſtreit charge for execution of iuſtice, becauſe he knowes that the power of gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is as well <hi>onus</hi> as <hi>honos,</hi> a <hi>burden,</hi> as an <hi>honour,</hi> ordeined for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:3592:22"/>and vninerſall <hi>welfare</hi> of all his ſubiects,<note place="margin">Salus populiſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ms le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> eſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> whereof account muſt be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to God. And he is alwaies in his owne eſtimation <hi>Magnus reip. ſeruus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Colimus Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratorem, vt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a Deo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum, &amp; ſole Deo minorem. Tertu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. ad Scap. Super Impera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nox eſt, niſi ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lus Deus qui fecit Imperate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Optat. contr. Parmenian. lib. <hi>3</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>the great ſeruant of the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-weale;</hi> for place and authoritie aduanced, and <hi>that most worthily,</hi> aboue all both perſons and ſtates; and yet in prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly clemency reſpectiue of the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, like a <hi>kind Maſter,</hi> or<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Homer. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Xe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noph.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Gueua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a. <hi>good Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For a good King differs nothing from a good Father:</hi> who, as he is <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ximus,</hi> the <hi>greateſt,</hi> ſo is he <hi>optimus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m vllum ſuper terra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> non babet. Chryſoſt. ad pop. Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>och. ham: <hi>2.</hi> Patriae parens.</note> the <hi>best;</hi> a <hi>common,</hi> yea an vniuerſall <hi>good,</hi> who promoteth peace and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like welfare, accounting all his feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie, <hi>as he is a Prince,</hi> to conſiſt in well-gouerning his Common-weale, and in beſtowing his life, for the good thereof (if need require) as the <hi>Emperor Alexander Seuerus</hi> profeſſed of himſelfe.</p>
               <p>Now then, as it is the higheſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnitie, and moſt neerely annexed to the <hi>Royall Crowne</hi> of a <hi>Chriſtian Prince</hi> to haue the title of preroga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiue
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:3592:22"/>to be <hi>Defender</hi> of the Chriſtian <hi>Faith,</hi> and to haue <hi>ſupreme authoritie</hi> ouer all cauſes and perſons <hi>Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall</hi> and <hi>Ciuill:</hi> ſo it apperteineth to him by that high authoritie to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt his care for the common good, as in making and executing of good and lawes for the promoting and eſtabliſhing of Religion, and Iuſtice:<note place="margin">Rex quia h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mo eſt, D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mino ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>it viuen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deliter: quia v. ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tiam R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>x eſt, ſeruit, l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ges iuſta praec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s &amp; con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a prohibentes, conuenienti vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gore ſanciendo. Aug: epiſt: <hi>50.</hi> ad Boniſa. ium. Idem contra Creſconium l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>51.</hi>
                  </note> ſo alſo in electing good Delegates, and competent Iudges and Miniſters of iuſtice: and in charging and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging them by all bond of dutie to vſe their authoritie to promote the publike good, in examining and deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all cauſes and controuerſies, with righteous iudgement and due execution of iuſtice, which is the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry life and ſoule of good and whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome lawes.</p>
               <p>And thus much of the <hi>perſon</hi> who gaue the <hi>Charge,</hi> GOD &amp; the KING: Now of the perſons to whom the Charge was <hi>giuen, Iudges and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Your Iudges.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">II. Point.</note> That is not onely
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:3592:23"/>Iudges in the moſt ſtrict and ſtreit notion &amp; ſignification of the phraſe; but <hi>all Magiſtrates</hi> alſo and Miniſters of iuſtice; at leaſt, by true and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie conſequence.</p>
               <p>And moſt meete it is ſurely that ſuch a ſtrict charge ſhould be giuen by God and the chiefe Ruler,<note place="margin">Doctr.</note> to ſuch as were elected and deſigned to be Iudges. For they are, for <hi>trust, kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of the Law;</hi> and, for their <hi>office, ſpeaking lawes;</hi> and, by their power and authoritie vnder God and the King, principall <hi>ſwayers</hi> and <hi>diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers</hi> of equitie and iuſtice. And as <hi>Maſters</hi> and <hi>Pilots</hi> in the <hi>ſhip</hi> of the <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> who ſit at the <hi>ſterne</hi> and <hi>guide</hi> it forward, through their wiſdome and fidelitie, in an euen, a proſperous, and ſucceſfull <hi>courſe,</hi> vnto the deſired <hi>hauen</hi> of peace and proſperitie: But through their care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe neglect and heedleſſe ouer-ſight, they cauſe fearefull <hi>ſhipwracke</hi> and miſerable ruine.</p>
               <p>And you know right well, that
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3592:23"/>when <hi>Iudges</hi> and Magiſtrates become <hi>wiſe</hi> and <hi>faithfull,</hi> in deliberate <hi>ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xion</hi> and due <hi>execution</hi> of good and wholſome <hi>lawes</hi> and <hi>ſtatutes,</hi> that then, by <hi>their</hi> good meanes, and <hi>Gods</hi> good bleſſing, Gods lawes are backed, his ordinances eſtabliſhed, piety is promoted, equitie preſerued, the Church is made pious, the Common-wealth proſperous, our communion with God and ſocietie with man becomes moſt comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, happy, and bleſſed. But when <hi>Rulers</hi> and Magiſtrates doe <hi>ſwerue</hi> in gouernment, growing careleſſe &amp; negligent, vngodly &amp; vniuſt, abuſing their authoritie or neglecting their dutie; then thorough the iuſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>God,</hi> and malice of the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill,</hi> and the vnbridled <hi>furie,</hi> and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded <hi>outrage</hi> of lewd, and ſauage, and vnreaſonable <hi>men,</hi> all things in Church and Common-wealth grow diſordered and confuſed, and finally fall (vnleſſe godly wiſdom in Rulers timely preuent) into fearefull ruine,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:3592:24"/>and dreadfull deſolation.</p>
               <p>Wherefore for the prudent pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenting of this ſo fearefull euill, and prouident procuring of that ſo hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full good, all Rulers and Magiſtrates, yea all miniſters of iuſtice, (Sheriffes, Counſellors, Aduocates, Iurors, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, and the reſt) (who are but <hi>men,</hi> and ſubiect to <hi>ſliding,</hi> of wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or weakneſſe) had neede to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue their charge and direction, from God and the King, for the better diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of this important buſineſſe, for the glory of God, who hath high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exalted them, and for the good of others, ouer whom he hath ſet them: for <hi>quò ſublimior gloria est,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cyprian.</note> 
                  <hi>eo maior &amp; cura eſt, the higher is their honour, the greater ought to be their care,</hi> and inlargeth the ſumme of their future account:<note place="margin">Hieron epiſt. ad Heliodorum de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ae ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tariae.</note> for <hi>cui plus creditur, plus ab eo exigitur; to whom more is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, of him more is exacted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>III. Point.</hi> The nature of the thing gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, a Charge.</note>And thus much of the <hi>perſons,</hi> to whom this Charge was <hi>giuen:</hi> Now I proceede to the <hi>third</hi> particular;
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:3592:24"/>which is, the <hi>nature</hi> and qualitie of this thing, which <hi>Moſes</hi> gaue to the Iudges, which is a <hi>command,</hi> a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, or a charge. <hi>I charged your Iudges.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now this being a <hi>Charge</hi> giuen of God and the King,<note place="margin">Doctr.</note> who are in degree the higheſt, it doth <hi>charge the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> in the higheſt degree, &amp; exacteth imployment both of body &amp; minde, for the exact diſcharg of this office &amp; dutie; and that in ſuch ſort, that an approued account may be well and readily made, not only to the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>principall Ruler,</hi> but alſo to <hi>God</hi> himſelfe, the <hi>King of Kings, and Iudge of Iudges,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.25.</note> euen the <hi>Iudge of the whole world.</hi> And for this cauſe it is religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly prouided, that an <hi>oath</hi> of the King, yea of the Lord is adminiſtred to inferior <hi>Iudges,</hi> yea to Iurors and witneſſes, the miniſters and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of iuſtice, for the faithfull diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of this weighty duty, ſo heaui-charging, if not ouer-charging, the ſoules and conſciences of all, who
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:3592:25"/>beare any part in the matter of iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>Wherefore,<note place="margin">Vſe.</note> by vertue of this Charge, let all be admoniſhed who haue the leaſt finger in matters of iuſtice (for it doth not concerne the Reuerend <hi>Iudges</hi> alone) let all (I ſay) be admoniſhed in the name of the Lord to account themſelues charged to ſuch performance of dutie, as whereof they muſt be accountant to God and the King. And therefore let religious care be had of all both Iudges, miniſters and inſtruments ſo to demeane and behaue themſelues, as ſincere and faithfull ſeruants of God, and truſly and loyall ſubiects to the King, that they may receiue for their paines, to their <hi>credit</hi> and <hi>comfort,</hi> both <hi>humane</hi> and <hi>diuine</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe and commendation.</p>
               <p>And thus much of the <hi>nature</hi> of this ſpeach, in that it is a <hi>Charge.</hi> Now time and deſire do haſten mee forward to conſider the <hi>time</hi> when this Charge was giuen.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:3592:25"/>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>IV. Point.</hi> The time whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this charge was giuen.</note> 
                  <hi>[At that time]</hi> that is, aſſoone as theſe were elected Iudges. In the fortieth yeare, the eleuenth moneth, and the firſt day, after their depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture out of Aegypt. Two moneths and a few daies before their entrance into the land of Canaan, where this their authoritie was to be exerciſed; and not ſo long before the death of <hi>Moſes</hi> the ſeruant of God, their prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall Ruler, who dyed the twelfth day of the twelfth moneth, as may be collected out of <hi>Deut.</hi> 34. &amp; <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 1. &amp; 4.</p>
               <p>O conſider, I beſeech you, this charge of <hi>Moſes</hi> to the Iudges, how fit, how <hi>timely,</hi> how ſeaſonable it was.</p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>Aſſoone</hi> as they were ſelected and deſigned to this office, that they might deliberately meditate and fore-bethinke themſelues of their dutie and charge.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Before</hi> execution of any part of their function, that in the beginning thereof they might lay ſuch a good
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:3592:26"/>foundation, that they might the more hopefully expect ſucceſſefull proceedings.</p>
               <p n="3">3 A little <hi>before their entrance</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the land of Canaan (their promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed land) that their inherita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce might not be polluted through violation of iuſtice, in their firſt poſſeſſion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and habitation therein.</p>
               <p n="4">4 And a <hi>little before the death of Moſes,</hi> their chiefe Prince and Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuer, that they might not be left de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of direction for matters of iudgement, after the loſſe of ſo wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie a Gouernour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wherefore timely and ſeaſonable ought to be the charge which Kings and Princes giue to their Delegates,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Doctr.</note> 
                  <hi>the Iudges and Magiſtrates:</hi> and which <hi>Iudges and Magiſtrates</hi> giue to the <hi>People</hi> their inferiours; euen in the <hi>entrance</hi> of their function, <hi>before</hi> exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, that they may not ſwerue from iuſtice, through ignorance, for want of direction; nor tranſgreſſe through preſumption, for want of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:3592:26"/>admonition. And ſo timely and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ought to be the charge, inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and admonitions of <hi>Parents</hi> to their children, of <hi>Maiſters</hi> to their ſeruants, and of all <hi>Superiors</hi> to infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors vnder their charge. But to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie my ſelfe onely to this, this time and occaſion.</p>
               <p>I onely obſerue that its prudently prouided (which is conſtantly pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed) that our reuerend Iudges of Aſſiſe (hauing receiued firſt inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from the King) make way in their entrance vnto iudicial proceſſe,<note place="margin">Vſe.</note> by giuing of their charge: wherein they doe with great learning and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie, giue ſuch wiſe directions, ſuch graue admonitions, and ſuch need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and ſeaſonable exhortations to the bodie of the Common-weale, whom theſe buſineſſes doe concern: that vnleſſe men be <hi>ſimple,</hi> they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be <hi>ignorant,</hi> and vnleſſe they be wilfull, they ſhall not make <hi>default,</hi> in diſcharge of the duetie and office wherein they are imployed.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:3592:27"/>
And ſo much of the <hi>firſt</hi> generall part of this text, the <hi>giuing of the charge.</hi> Now I come to the <hi>ſecond,</hi> and principally intended, <hi>the Charge which was giuen;</hi> the tenour where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is this: <hi>Heare the cauſes betweene your Brethren, and iudge righteouſly, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>Second generall Part. The Charge giuen.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>I. Point.</hi> Inſtructions, and Imuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note>In this charge giuen, there come firſt to our view, the <hi>Inſtructions</hi> and <hi>Iniunctions,</hi> which are giuen to the Iudges, which are in number two:
<list>
                     <item>to heare deliberately.</item>
                     <item>to iudge righteouſly.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>And for preparing of our paſſage to the handling of them, wee are to conſider by way of Preface: Firſt, what are the <hi>Cauſes</hi> to be heard and iudged: Secondly, what is the <hi>Rule</hi> of righteous iudgement.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> For the <hi>firſt:</hi> the <hi>Cauſes</hi> which fall into the conſideration of Iudges,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:3592:27"/>are (by <hi>Plato</hi>) reduced to two heads:<note place="margin">Omnia iudicia aut diſtrahen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darum contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rum, aut puniend orum maleficiorum cauſa reperiae ſunt. In diſceptan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> controuerſijs, tuenda diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plina. Iuſtinian.</note> to doe <hi>Iniurie:</hi> to doe <hi>Euill:</hi> and (as <hi>Cicero</hi> doth accordingly write) All iudgement was deuiſed eyther firſt for the <hi>deciding of controuerſies,</hi> or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, <hi>puniſhment of malefactors.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The matters then (as our reuerend Iudges alſo tell vs) are <hi>Ciuill,</hi> or <hi>Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minall,</hi> that concerne <hi>right</hi> betweene man and man, or puniſhment of <hi>crimos.</hi> And therefore to giue to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one his owne, and to redreſſe iniuries is a principal office of iuſtice <hi>diſtributiue.</hi> And to puniſh malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors in cauſes criminall, is an office of iuſtice <hi>vindicatiue,</hi> as neceſſarie for the good of the common-wealth as the other. Now this charge is to be obſerued in all kinds of cauſes, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>treſpaſſes</hi> or <hi>crimes:</hi> 1. <hi>heare:</hi> 2. <hi>iudge</hi> righteouſly. 2. The <hi>rule</hi> of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous iudgement is the <hi>Law;</hi> for the <hi>Law</hi> is a <hi>ſilent magiſtrate,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate</hi> a <hi>ſpeaking Law:</hi> Now the Law, this rule of iudgement, is <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane,</hi> or <hi>Diuine;</hi> and the order for
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:3592:28"/>conformitie of iudgement muſt bee this.</p>
               <p>Mans Law muſt bee ſubordinate to Gods Law; the Iudges ſentence to mans Law, and therewithall to Gods Law.<note place="margin">Leges cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fuerint inſtit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tae non licebit indici de ipſisſed ſecundu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ipſas <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>dicare. Aug.</note> 
                  <hi>Lawes beeing once well eſtabliſhed, the Iudge muſt not iudge of them, but by them,</hi> as an <hi>Interpreter</hi> or them: and the Interpreter muſt haue the ſame meaning with the Law ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker; otherwiſe (wreſting wordes ſtrictly, contrary to the meaning) <hi>ſummum ius</hi> becomes <hi>ſumma iniuria,</hi> ſtrickt law, flat iniuſtice.</p>
               <p>Theſe things being premiſed, the directions or iniunctions giuen to the Iudges are two: firſt, to heare; and ſeconde, to iudge. Within which three degrees of iudiciall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe (which is the lawfull handling of the action) are included or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized: firſt, <hi>Hearing;</hi> ſecondly, <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſing;</hi> thirdly, <hi>ſentencing</hi> of cauſes: vpon which (as a conſequent) fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes <hi>execution:</hi> or thus, firſt <hi>hearing</hi> of the cauſe, ſecondly, <hi>giuing</hi> of the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:3592:28"/>
                  <hi>ſentence,</hi> thirdly, <hi>execution</hi> of the ſentence pronounced; which ſome take to be meant by that clauſe, <hi>Yee ſhall not feare the face of man.</hi> But vnder correction, wee may take it thus: Theſe duties as three degrees in iudiciall proceſſe, are giuen in charge by <hi>Moſes</hi> to the Iudges: firſt to <hi>heare</hi> cauſes wiſely and deliberate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: ſecondly, to <hi>ſentence</hi> the cauſes heard, iuſtly and equally: thirdly, to <hi>execute</hi> iudgement according to ſentence giuen faithfully and exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: or more briefely thus;</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Three degrees in iudiciall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe.</note>The iudiciall proceſſe hath three de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees; to heare iuſtice; ſpeake iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice; doe iuſtice.</p>
               <p>To which are required three things in a Iudge, an eye of knowledge, a tongue of truth, an hand of power. And this is alſo the order to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued therein.</p>
               <p n="1">1 There muſt <hi>firſt</hi> be hearing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſentence be giuen, elſe how can the ſentence be iuſt?</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Sentence</hi> muſt be giuen before
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:3592:29"/>execution be done, elſe how can the execution be warrantable?</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Execution</hi> muſt follow vppon ſentence giuen, elſe to what is ſuch proceſſe profitable? But when cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are deliberately and diſcerningly <hi>heard,</hi> ſo as the truth is ſeene as in the cleare glaſſe of wiſedome: when <hi>Sentence</hi> is iuſtly and equally giuen, as the cauſe beares weight in the bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance of equitie. And when ſentence is throughly and exactly <hi>executed,</hi> as with a ſharpe ſword of ſufficient power, then are theſe iniunctions and directions of <hi>Moſes</hi> faithfully obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and ſufficiently performed.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The firſt degree. To heare iuſtice.</note>The firſt degree in iudiciall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe is the <hi>hearing of iuſtice,</hi> or of the cauſe to be iudged: and this muſt needes be firſt; elſe no iuſt ſentence can be giuen. Right iudgement doth preſuppoſe ſure knowledge. You know the ſaying; <hi>Si iudicas, cognoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce: If yee will iudge,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Senec. Trag.</note> 
                  <hi>take notice of the cauſe,</hi> for the cauſe muſt be knowen before it can bee iudged, and firſt
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:3592:29"/>heard, that it may be knowne.<note place="margin">Qui ſtatuit ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid parte in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>audita altera, aequum licet ſtatuerit haud aequus erit. Senec. Plaut. Gen. <hi>11.5.</hi> Non humano modo hoc in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligamus, ſed vt per hoc eru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diamur, nun q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> temerè fratres condemnandos, ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> auditu ſolo iudicandu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, niſi pluribus argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tis priùs certi reddamur. Omnia enim ideo à Deo fiunt &amp; ob hoc tantâ ad erudiendum humanu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> genus vtitur ſermonis attempera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ione. Gen. <hi>18.</hi> v. <hi>20.</hi> v. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> And <hi>he that ſhall giue ſentence, eyther partie not firſt herd, though his ſentence proue equall, yet is hee not an equall Iudge.</hi> The <hi>Lord</hi> himſelfe obſerues this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of proceſſe, where its ſayd <hi>That God went downe to ſee the Citie and Tower</hi> which the Nimrodians had builded. On which place <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> doth well obſerue, that Gods ſpirit doth declare by an <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (or humane kind of ſpeech) that men ought not to condemne their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren before certain knowledge and notice of their cauſe. And before the finall ſentence of deſtruction bee paſſed on <hi>Sodome,</hi> the Lord firſt takes notice of their eſtate; ſaying; <hi>Becauſe the crye of Sodome and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrha is great, and becauſe their ſin is very grieuous; I will goe downe now, and ſee whether they haue done altogether according to the crye of it: which is come to mee: and if not, I will know.</hi> The Lord who knew all things of himſelfe, will alſo take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:3592:30"/>as by iudiciall proceſſe, thereby, as in a Table, to commend to our view, as in a liuely <hi>picture</hi> or perfect patterne, the order to bee obſerued in iudiciall proceedings for humane profit and conſtant imitation. And thus God firſt heard the Iſraelites <hi>groane vnder the burdens of Aegypt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 22.23<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 24.</note> and then, and not before, he ſent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance.</p>
               <p>To <hi>teach</hi> all Iudges,<note place="margin">Doctr.</note> who beare Gods-Image and title in their office, to follow him, as their patterne in the execution thereof; not precipitating ſentence before due conſideration, &amp; well-weighing, and diſcerning the equitie of the cauſe: for if God did ſo, who is the knower of all things, who cannot be deceyued, miſled, or corrupted; much more ought men giue diligence hereunto, who are daily ſubiect to be miſtaken, through ouer-ſight, to bee miſled by affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, tranſported through paſſion, precipitated with preiudice, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued with colourable pretences, and gloſſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:3592:30"/>
But here I ſhall not need to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to our reuerend, godly, and well-experienced <hi>Moderators</hi> of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, but onely poynt at ſuch things, as they know, and which, on occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I haue ſometimes obſerued, to be religiouſly practiſed, in their iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall proceſſe: and this I ſhall the rather be bould to ſpeake, that inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours of leſſe, both knowledge, expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience and conſcience, may take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of ſuch vertues, for due appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of them in their betters, and reſpectiue imitation of them in themſelues.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Hearing is ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther 1. ſimple hearing. 2. Diſcuſſing.</note>Now this hearing which tends to the notice of the cauſe, is eyther a <hi>ſimple</hi> hearing of both the parties, or elſe an accurate <hi>diſcuſsing,</hi> and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining of their euidences and proofes.</p>
               <p>The firſt is the equall <hi>hearing</hi> of all perſons, both <hi>actor &amp; reus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Hearing.</note> plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tife and defendant, <hi>Small as well as great.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ier 26. v. 2.3.4.12.16.</note> This was obſerued in the arraignement of <hi>Ieremiah</hi> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:3592:31"/>whom the Prieſts and Prophets apprehended and conuented before the Iudges, and accuſed capitally as worthie of death, for denouncing Gods iudgements againſt Iuda at Gods command: <hi>Ieremiahs</hi> defence was accordingly heard, &amp; he acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Princes and Iudges.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 18.29.</note> 
                  <hi>Pilate</hi> thus farre demeaned himſelfe well in the caſe of our Sauiour, while hee would not giue credite to the high-Prieſts accuſation, but would heare the poore defendant, as well as theſe plaintifes, though men of chief place and authoritie amongſt them. <hi>Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demus</hi> did reaſon like a worthie Iudge, and prudent Magiſtrate; <hi>Doth our Law condemne any man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it heare him,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 7.51.</note> 
                  <hi>and know what hee doth?</hi> But the reſt, his vniuſt and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equall Brethren, did <hi>take him vppe</hi> very ſharpely for it, and reſolued to condemne Chriſt abſent, and vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>heard in his iuſt defence; whereas the moſt groſſe, and moſt vile male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor ought firſt to be conuicted, by
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:3592:31"/>
                  <hi>two witneſſes</hi> at the leaſt (<hi>Deutr.</hi> 19.15.) before ſentence of iudgement be paſſed againſt him.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Demoſth. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Ante meridi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m cauſam conſcito cum perorarint ambo praeſentes. <hi>12.</hi> Tab.</note> 
                  <hi>Hee that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth a matter before it be heard, it is folly and ſhame vnto him, ſaith the Wiſeman. Prou.</hi> 18.13.</p>
               <p>It was the equitie of the Iudges by the law of the <hi>Athenians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ne: viſum nec auditum homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem damnare nefas vlti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um cenſetur; Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. Marcel. Nulla maior iniuria quam indictâ cauſâ aliquem iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care.</note> to hear both parties alike. And an Iniunction ſet downe in the 12. <hi>Tables,</hi> at auncient Rome: <hi>Before mid-day take notice of the cauſe when both the perſons in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence haue pleaded.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And it was alwaies accounted a moſt haynous offence,<note place="margin">Lucianus. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Plato in Demodico ex Poeta.</note> 
                  <hi>to ſentence, or condemne men, their cauſes not firſt heard.</hi> And prudent prouiſion is made by all good lawes, that <hi>iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment bee not giuen before the cauſe bee heard.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>2. Diſcuſſing.</hi> Iudicantem o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portet cuncta rimari, et ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem rerum ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na inquiſitione decurrere, quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſque ad veritatem per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniatur. E lentherius.</note>
               </p>
               <p>As there muſt be a <hi>ſimple</hi> equall hearing of both the parties; ſo muſt there be an accurate <hi>examination</hi> and exquiſite <hi>diſcuſsing</hi> of the cauſe. This is the law of God. <hi>Deutr.</hi> 13. <hi>ver.</hi> 12.13. That if the Iudge haue heard of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:3592:32"/>an abhomination done (as the ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of Gods people) <hi>he muſt inquire, make ſearch</hi> &amp; ask, and <hi>that diligently,</hi> (great is the emphaſis and weight of the words) and if it bee found cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely true, then muſt hee puniſh. <hi>Deutr.</hi> 17.4.5.6.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioſhuah.</hi> 7.22. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.43. <hi>Ionah.</hi> 1.8.10.</note> 
                  <hi>Ioſhuah</hi> would not condemne <hi>Achan</hi> vpon Gods Lot, and his owne confeſſion, vntill hee found (by ſearch) his confeſſion to be true: Not <hi>Saul Ionathan;</hi> nor the <hi>Mariners Ionah</hi> taken by lot, vntill examination and hearing of their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer and defence:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 7.</note> and <hi>Nicodemus</hi> doth take it an expreſſe poynt in Gods Law, That a man ought not to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned vpon bare hearing, no not till it bee knowne what hee hath done. Thus did righteous <hi>Iob,</hi> in his legall proceſſe. <hi>The cauſe that I knew not, I ſearched out, Iob.</hi> 29.16. And thus farre did <hi>Pilate</hi> well in the cauſe of Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 25.27. <hi>Act.</hi> 24 22.27.</note> 
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 18.30. And <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi> the Preſident of <hi>Caeſaria,</hi> and <hi>Foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lix</hi> his Predeceſſor in the caſe of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul.</hi> And <hi>Salomons</hi> wiſedome was
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:3592:32"/>experienced and admired in that firſt caſe of the two harlots, who conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for the child,<note place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 3.</note> when after ſtrict examination, through a wiſe inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſemblance of diuiding the quicke childe, he did extort a confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from the true mother, by ſtrange commotion of her naturall affection. And God himſelfe doth often incul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate this as the dutie of the Iudge: <hi>The Iudges ſhall make diligent inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deutr.</hi> 29.18.</note> and for this cauſe they had neede both to haue, and vſe thoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent parts of wiſdome and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, which God requireth of them, and beſtoweth vpon them. <hi>Deutr.</hi> 1.13.</p>
               <p>How needfull and helpfull in iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall proceſſe is the exquiſite and accurate diſcuſſing of the cauſe, it may appeare by this; that the more exactly the cauſe is diſcerned and knowne, the more iuſt ſentence may thereof be giuen, as Great <hi>Demoſthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> did well obſerue.</p>
               <p>Wherefore there are required (as
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:3592:33"/>you know right well) in a Iudge or Magiſtrate in hearing of cauſes, that they may be equally heard and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitely diſcuſſed,<note place="margin">Things to be obſerued in hearing of cauſes.</note> ſundry things to be obſerued and practiſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Serious <hi>attention</hi> to the matter in hand, that no materiall proofe or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant reaſon, tending to euince the equitie of the cauſe, through heedles neglect be omitted or let paſſe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out obſeruation and notice taken thereof. For as one well learned and experienced ſaith well:<note place="margin">In eo ſape quod aures praeterve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum eſt, ſtatus cauſae verſatur. Joan. Bodin. de repub.</note> 
                  <hi>In that oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times which paſſeth by the eare, doth the ſtate of the cauſe conſist.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Wiſe <hi>moderation</hi> and ordering of the proceſſe; that impertinent di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, odious invectiues, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnious imputations among plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders or witneſſes, vſed to prejudice the contrary perſon or cauſe, be ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably interrupted, and ſharply re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, and that neither party be hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, by his aduerſaries raſh inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, and cauſed to omit, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale, what may make for his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:3592:33"/>and to cleare the equitie of his iuſt and equall cauſe. It is the part of the <hi>Pleader</hi> or Aduocate,<note place="margin">Ariſt. lib. Rhet.</note> onely to <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare</hi> whether the thing be ſo or not ſo, done or not done; whether <hi>iuſt</hi> or vniuſt the <hi>Iudge</hi> himſelfe muſt know.</p>
               <p>And here I deſire the learned and experienced Moderators of iuſtice to conſider, whether (for the moſt part) the <hi>wrong-doer</hi> be not the more pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſh and clamorous, and beſt armed with Pleaders and Aduocates againſt the innocent?</p>
               <p>There muſt be invincible <hi>patience,</hi> and vnweariable forbearance, of the ſlowneſſe of ſpeach, dulneſſe of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, rudeneſſe of behauiour, and other infirmities and weakneſſes of many the meaner and inferior ſort, whoſe teſtimonies for others, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences for themſelues, in iudiciall proceſſe, are of neceſſitie required. Such wants and defects muſt be paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by with charitable <hi>forbearance</hi> and compaſſionate reſpect.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:3592:34"/>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> All <hi>vnquiet affections</hi> and inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate paſſions, of hatred, loue, enuie, an ger, raſh zeale, or the like, muſt be quite put off, and wholy laid aſide. <hi>Deſire and anger are ill Counſellors, worſe Iudges.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Conſultores ſunt p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſimi cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pido &amp; ira. Saluſt. Amor turbat conſtia. Hieron.</note> 
                  <hi>Loue troubleth counſels. Enuie neuer ſpeakes well</hi> (that is iuſtly) ſaith our common <hi>Prouerbe.</hi> Yea, all inordinate affections blind the eyes, and preiudice iudgement, and therefore all dealers in iudgement, eſpecially the chiefe ſwayers, muſt ſpeake <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>without affections.</hi> It was the oath of the <hi>Heathen</hi> Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, as the Orator doth report:<note place="margin">Audiam accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um fine affectibus &amp; perſonarum r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſpectione. Demoſth.</note> 
                  <hi>I will heare the plaintiffe and defendant with an equall mind, without affections and reſpect of perſons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Not to inſiſt particularly on more particulars, there muſt be firmeneſſe of <hi>memory</hi> to recall ſuch euidences as were of moſt moment on either be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe; and <hi>wiſdome</hi> and knowledge, and a kind of <hi>dexteritie</hi> in conferring and comparing cauſe with cauſe, and reaſon with reaſon; and <hi>iudgement</hi>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:3592:34"/>and learned <hi>skill</hi> in the lawes, both di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine &amp; humane, to weigh the proofes in the ballance of iuſtice, and to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne and diſtinguiſh of iuſt and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt, that ſo the cauſe may be fitted for ſentence: elſe cannot the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence proue iuſt and equall,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſai.</hi> 5.20.</note> but <hi>good ſhall be called euill, and euill good;</hi> the wicked ſhall be abſolued, the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent condemned. For that of <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> is certainly true, <hi>Ignorantia Iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis est calamitas innocentis:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. de Ciuit. Dei l. cap. <hi>29.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>The igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the Iudge is the calamitie of the innocent.</hi> It was the ſpeach of a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned man,<note place="margin">Quis est qui neſcit tam mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta in boni iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis officio poſita eſſe, vt ſeritiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos etiam ac di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligentiſſimos fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giant?</note> very well ſeene and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced in this kind; <hi>Who knowes not that ſo many things are required in the office of a good Iudge, that they eaſily eſcape the most skilfull and diligent?</hi> And therefore in a word,<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>I</label> to conclude this point, all the will and skill, vſe and exerciſe of heart and eare, body and mind, had neede to be imployed in hearing of cauſes; that all the weight, of right or wrong, being put into the ballance of equitie and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:3592:35"/>it may be diſcerned, by the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding Iudge, which of the ſcales is of greater poiſe and weight.</p>
               <p>But for want of theſe and ſuch like obſeruations in this firſt degree of iudiciall proceſſe,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Vſe.</hi>
                  </note> there was much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtice and ſin committed by Iudges and Magiſtrates in the caſe of<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 39.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph,</hi> of<note n="b" place="margin">2 <hi>Sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> 16.13.</note> 
                  <hi>Mephiboſheth,</hi> of<note n="c" place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 21.13.</note> 
                  <hi>Naboth,</hi> of<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Am s</hi> 7.10.</note> 
                  <hi>Amos,</hi> of<note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.59, 60.</note> 
                  <hi>Christ Ieſus,</hi> of<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 6.13, 14.</note> 
                  <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phan,</hi> of<note n="g" place="margin">Theodor hiſt. Eccleſ. l <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>29.</hi> Socrat. lib. <hi>1.</hi> c.</note> 
                  <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> and very many others, as Hiſtories do record, and experience doth declare.</p>
               <p>And thus much of the firſt degree of iudiciall proceſſe, of the <hi>hearing</hi> of iuſtice: Now I proceede to the ſecond degree, which is the <hi>ſpeaking</hi> of iuſtice: <hi>and iudge righteouſly.</hi>]</p>
               <p>After the cauſe is diſcerningly heard,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>The II. Degree.</hi> To ſpeake iuſtice.</note> then is iudgment to be iuſtly giuen, and ſentence to be equally pronounced:<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>not according to affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and fauour; but according to iuſtice and truth:</hi> according to the preſcript of wholſome law, which is the <hi>ſquare
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:3592:35"/>of equitie;</hi> the law (I ſay) of <hi>Man,</hi> and the law of <hi>God.</hi> For as the law of the King, who is the Head of the Common-wealth, is the life of this bodie Politike: ſo is the law of God the ſoule of the law of the King; and as the law of the king ought to be conformed to the law of God, which is the right rule indeed of equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and iuſtice: ſo the ſentence of the Iudge muſt be conformed to the law of God, and the King, that it may be an equall ſentence. For the <hi>Law</hi> is nothing elſe but <hi>a ſilent Magiſtrate,</hi> and the <hi>Magiſtrate, a ſpeaking law,</hi> or a ſpeaker of law. And a Iudge or Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice is a ſpeaker of iuſtice, and <hi>iudico</hi> is <hi>ius dico.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Judex hine di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus, quod ius populis dicat, quod iure diſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptet, id eſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> iudicet: iudex in quo iuſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tia deſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ratur, eſſe nequeat Iudex Iſidor.</note> And therefore <hi>a Iudge or Iuſtice, in whom iuſtice is not, is not a Iudge,</hi> but by equiuocation. It is the injunction of the law diuine: <hi>Iudges and officers ſhalt thou make: and they ſhall iudge the people with iuſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Thou ſhalt not wreſt iudgment. That which is altogether iuſt ſhalt thou follow.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deutr.</hi> 6. <hi>v.</hi> 18, 19, 20.</note> Worthy an Emperor was
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:3592:36"/>the profeſſion of <hi>Iuſtinian,</hi> which I would commend to your godly imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation:<note place="margin">Aequam me vtrique parti, tam in diſcep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tandis contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſiis, quam in tuenda diſcipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nâ praebebo. N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>utri par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i praeter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; ſas ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ctꝰ ero. quod ſi haec non o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ro, onu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modis ero exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitus, tam hic quara in futuro ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ulo, in borrè<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> do indicio ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gni Domini Dei &amp; ſalu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>toris n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtri Ieſu Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſii: habeboque parte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cum Iuda, &amp; lepram c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m Huzziah, &amp; trem rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> cum Cain.</note> 
                  <hi>Aequu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me vtri<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> parti tam in diſceptandis co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouerſiis, quam in tuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da diſciplina praebebo</hi> &amp;c. <hi>I will ſhew my ſelfe equall to both parties; as well in deciding of controuerſies, as in defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of diſcipline. I will fauour neither part beyond law and right, and if I ſhall not obſerue theſe things, I ſhall be expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to all diſcommodities, both here and in the world to come, in that dreadfull iudgement of our great Lord God, and our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, and I ſhall haue my portion with Iudas, the leproſie with Huzziah, and trembling with Cain.</hi> O memorable ſentence wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be ingrauen in the very heart of Iudges and Magiſtrates, with the point of a Diamond, yea with the finger of Gods ſpirit. And ſo much of this.</p>
               <p>Now we are come to the laſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of the dutie of a Iudge in iudi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciall proceſſe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>The</hi> 3 <hi>Degree.</hi> To do iuſtice.</note> which is the <hi>doing of iuſtice,</hi> or <hi>execution</hi> of iudgment pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:3592:36"/>
After the cauſe is diſcerningly <hi>heard</hi> with the eare of iuſtice, and the <hi>ſentence</hi> equally pronounced with the mouth of iuſtice, then muſt <hi>exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution</hi> be exactly done by the hand of iuſtice; both in rendring to euery man his right, and alſo in freeing the innocent, and puniſhing malefactors. For vnleſſe this exact <hi>execution</hi> do follow, the former proceſſe is alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether fruitleſſe, and tends to no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit or good effect. But in matters of <hi>controuerſie</hi> the partie oppreſſed ſtands ſtill vnreleeued, after all his coſt and painefull trauaile. And in matters of <hi>crime,</hi> enormities and diſorders remaine ſtill vnreformed. And in both, both Church and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth ſtand fearefully ſurchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with the guilt of many ſinnes. And often for want of due execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of iudgement by the ſword of the Magiſtrate, the ſword of Gods wrath is vnſheathed againſt a Land; eſpecially for the releeuing of the helpleſſe oppreſſed, and in reuenging
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:3592:37"/>of bloody and crying ſins.</p>
               <p>And thus much of the inſtructions and injunctions giuen to the Iudges, and of the three degrees of iudiciall proceſſe, which are the three duties of a good and worthy Iudge.</p>
               <p>Now followeth the ſecond parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular obſerued in this Charge,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>II. Point.</hi> Parties be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene whom they muſt heare &amp; Iudge</note> name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>parties whoſe cauſes are to be heard and iudged,</hi> which are ſet out in relation: <hi>Firſt</hi> to the Iudges, <hi>your brethren. Secondly,</hi> among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues; <hi>Betweene euery man and his brother</hi>] that is, (as was ſaid) of the ſame Nation, of the ſame Religion: neither onely ſo, but of the ſame na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>And the ſtranger that is with him:</hi> a ſtranger for kindred, nation, or religion, is yet a brother for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon nature and humane condition, and muſt haue right done him as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a brother.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Your Brethren]</hi> The name <hi>brother</hi> is a name of ſpeciall relation, and notes out a ſpeciall vicinitie of one vnto another, and ſome degree of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:3592:37"/>equalitie one with another.</p>
               <p>The perſons whoſe cauſes are to be heard and iudged are <hi>brethren</hi> to the <hi>Iudge;</hi> not, indeed, in function, or equalitie of condition. For herein are Iudges and Magiſtrates exalted aboue them,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1.</note> and for this cauſe they owe reuerence and reſpect to the Iudges.</p>
               <p>As for <hi>Anabaptiſticall</hi> conceits,<note place="margin">Confutat.</note> which denie lawfull Magiſtracie, and would bring in vnſeemely paritie, and confuſed anarchie, they are to be vtterly renounced, and farre abando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned out of the hearts of all true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians; and that auncient <hi>law</hi> is to be embraced, which calleth it <hi>ſacriledge not to reuerence and obey the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate:</hi> and thoſe who do contemne the Magiſtrate, doe contemne euen <hi>God himſelfe</hi> (who is the ordeiner and mainteiner of magiſtracie) <hi>as the Lord himſelfe ſaith vnto Samuel.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.7.</note> Yet is the Iudge to account them his <hi>bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren: Brethren</hi> (I ſay) in common nature and humanitie, <hi>brethren</hi> (it
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:3592:38"/>may be) in grace and Chriſtianitie; <hi>brethren,</hi> both in humane condition, and chriſtian profeſſion.</p>
               <p>Which conſideration ought to ſtir vp <hi>Iudges</hi> and Magiſtrates vnto ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critie and cheerefulneſſe in execution of their function;<note place="margin">Doctr.</note> ſeeing all their imployments &amp; trauels therein tend to the good and profit of their <hi>bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</hi> Now what ſtudie is too vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſant? what trauaile too toyleſom? what labour too great? what time too long? what tolerancie too te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious, in procuring the weale and welfare of their <hi>brethren?</hi> Eſpecially, ſeeing they are ſet apart to this hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable imployment, by ordination and injunction of God and the King, who haue highly aduanced them aboue their brethren, to be Iudges and deciders of their perſons and cauſes.<note place="margin">Cypr.</note> 
                  <hi>Quo ſublimior gloria est, eo maior &amp; cura eſt: The higher is their glory, the greater ſhould be their care.</hi> Wherefore I beſeech you from the Lord, moſt reuerend Iudges, heare
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:3592:38"/>the cauſes, and iudge righteouſly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene your brethren, <hi>for they are your brethren.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if one only or ſome few were <hi>brethren</hi> to the Iudge, and not the reſt,<note place="margin">Nemo fere est, qui ſit bonus index in ſuis rebus. Ariſt. polit. lib. <hi>3.</hi> Inſitu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> est mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talibus cunctis, vt ſe &amp; ſua a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp; ſint benigni in ſuis cauſis. Senec. Lege decernimꝰ nemine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſibi eſſi indicem, aut ius dicere debere. Imper. Cod. lib. <hi>2.</hi> tit. <hi>5.</hi> Qui iuriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oni praeeſt ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſibi ius dicere d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bet, neque vxori, vel libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, vel caeteris quos ſecum ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet.</note> then were he not a fit and a competent Iudge, for then were the caſe in ſome ſort his owne, and <hi>few are fit Iudges in their owne cauſes. For its inbred in all mortall men, to loue themſelues and their owne things, and to be kind and fauourable in their owne cauſes.</hi> And therefore the auncient <hi>lawes</hi> of <hi>Emperors forbade that men ſhould be Iudges to giue ſentence for themſelues.</hi> And it is an aſſertion of that great Lawyer <hi>Vlpian,</hi> that no man ought to be Iudge for himſelfe, or his wife, or children, or the reſt that are neere vnto him.</p>
               <p>But now the parties are all <hi>brethren among themſelues,</hi> aſwell as to the Iudge; and that in nature, nation, and profeſſion of religion, as the Iewes were, and as we are. And why ſhould men contend, ſeeing they are
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:3592:39"/>
                  <hi>brethren?</hi> why ſhould men defraud, oppreſſe, rob, ſpoyle, maime or mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their <hi>brethren?</hi> It is a very great both ſin and ſhame, that men of the ſame Nation and language, who liue vnder the ſame King and lawes, who enjoy the ſame liberties and priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, who are linked together in neighbourhood and acquaintance; yea, who partake in the ſame com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munitie of grace and communion of glory, ſhould not liue in loue toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and <hi>keepe the vnitie of the ſpirit in the bond of peace,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ephef.</hi> 4 3.</note> but defraud, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe, and injure one another.</p>
               <p>And if, through their owne cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, and Satans malice, they fall at variance, diſcord and controuerſie, then ſurely ſuch as are deſigned and appointed by God and the King to performe and execute the moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable office and function of <hi>Iudges</hi> and Magiſtrates, ought to vſe their beſt endeauour, to compound con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies, to right wrongs, to puniſh crimes, and by all good meanes to
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:3592:39"/>procure both publike and priuate peace, that all men may liue ſafely, quietly and louingly together, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are brethren.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, ſuppoſe any be a ſtranger, for particular nation, or profeſſion of religion, yet is he ſtill a brother in <hi>common nature</hi> and humane condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and therefore muſt haue iuſtice done to him, as being a <hi>brother,</hi> both vnto the Iudge, and vnto his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Heare and iudge righteouſly between a man &amp; the ſtranger that is with him</hi>] All men were created one in nature, reaſonable creatures, all were inſtam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped with the image of God, all retaine their ſimple nature, though all haue not recouered Gods image, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine corrupted; and all muſt haue iuſtice, for its founded in nature. Yea and for a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Iudge not to doe iuſtice to an <hi>Ethnick</hi> or pagan conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding with a Chriſtian, were to abuſe his function, to blemiſh his religion, to harden the Pagan in his infidelitie
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:3592:40"/>and ſin: And not to right a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> contending with a <hi>Pagan</hi> were, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the abuſe of his function, to neglect his dutie to one deare to God. Fit it is that he ſhould receiue equitie and iuſtice at the hand of the Iudge, who hath found grace and mercy at the hand of God. Among the <hi>Iewes</hi> there was <hi>one Law for all, for the ſtranger, and for one of their countrey:</hi> if either ſinned, either muſt be puniſhed. <hi>Leuit.</hi> 24. <hi>v.</hi> 16, 22.</p>
               <p>The ſumme of all is this. All men are <hi>brethren</hi> to the <hi>Iudge</hi> himſelfe, therefore he muſt in loue and dutie labour to releeue them all. All are <hi>brethren</hi> amongſt <hi>themſelues,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he muſt haue equall reſpect for righting of them all.</p>
               <p>Wherefore, as <hi>Moſes</hi> from God ſaid to theſe Iudges, ſo I, from the ſame God, ſay vnto you all, moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend Iudges, and all miniſters of iuſtice, <hi>Heare and iudge righteouſly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene your brethren, and betweene euery man and his brother, and the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:3592:40"/>ſtranger that is with him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo much of the <hi>perſons:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>III. Point.</hi> Admonitions or Cautions.</note> Now I proceede to the <hi>third</hi> particular ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued in this charge, namely, <hi>The admonitions or cautions</hi> giuen to the Iudges, againſt peſtilent impediments which are frequent enemies to equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and iuſtice, which are in number two.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Acceptation</hi> of perſons, for ſini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter reſpects.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Feare</hi> of mens greatnes, who will be offended at iuſtice.</item>
               </list>
               <p>The former <hi>admonition</hi> or caution is againſt that principall impediment of iuſtice,<note place="margin">The firſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediment of iuſtice.</note> 
                  <hi>acceptation of perſons;</hi> which is ſet downe 1. <hi>Negatiuely,</hi> ſo that the vice is forbidden, <hi>Yee ſhall not reſpect perſons in iudgment.</hi> 2. <hi>Affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiuely,</hi> ſo that the vertue is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded; <hi>You ſhall heare the ſmall as well as the great.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Acceptation</hi> of perſons,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> vnjuſt and vnlawfull, is ſuch <hi>by and outward</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect had of the perſon, as doth <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing</hi> make for the <hi>equitie</hi> of the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:3592:41"/>cauſe; and yet drawes the Iudge, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror or witneſſe, or other miniſters of iuſtice, to doe <hi>vnequally</hi> in caſe of iudgement, by reaſon of his <hi>vnequall</hi> reſpect to the <hi>perſon:</hi> as when mens vnjuſt and vnequall cauſes are fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and furthered, for amitie, enmitie, hatred, or loue, for bribes, wealth, kindred, authoritie, or the like: and where cauſes are ouerthrowne and perſons condemned for want of friends, money, or ſuch outward re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, though their cauſes be iuſt or perſons innocent, or not deſeruing ſuch ſeueritie of cenſure. This accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of perſons is <hi>iudiciorum peſt is,</hi> the <hi>plague of iudgements,</hi> and flatly forbidden in Gods ſacred word, <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit.</hi> 19.15. <hi>Yee ſhall not doe vnrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly in iudgment, thou ſhalt not reſpect the perſon of the poore, nor honour the perſon of the mighty; but in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſhalt thou iudge thy neighbour.</hi> Partiall pitie is not to be ſhewed to the poore and baſe, becauſe he is poore and baſe: and partiall fauour
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:3592:41"/>is not to be ſhewed to the rich and honorable, becauſe he is rich or ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable: but according to the <hi>equitie</hi> of the <hi>cauſe,</hi> muſt be the <hi>equitie</hi> of the <hi>iudgment.</hi> Prohibitions of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary are frequent in Gods word: <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſpeake in a cauſe, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline after many, to wreſt iudgement;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.2, 3.</note> 
                  <hi>neither ſhalt thou countenance a poore man in his</hi> (vnrighteous) <hi>cauſe. It is not good</hi> (that is, it is very ill) <hi>to accept the perſon of the wicked,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pron.</hi> 18.5.</note> 
                  <hi>to ouerthrow the righteous in iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</hi> The like is found <hi>Prov.</hi> 24.23, 24. <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.21. The Lord doth deteſt this abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſinne <hi>Eſa.</hi> 61.8. <hi>I the Lord loue iudgment, and hate robbery for burnt offering:</hi> that is, though a thing got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by peruerting iudgement, were put to the beſt vie that can be, as to a ſacrifice to God, yet God doth ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre it. Yea the Lord <hi>accurſeth</hi> to the pit of Hell, ſuch as peruert the iudgment of the ſtranger, fatherleſſe, and widow <hi>Deutr.</hi> 27. And denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth a fearefull woe againſt them,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:3592:42"/>
                  <hi>who iuſtifie the wicked for a reward, and take away the righteouſneſſe of the righteous from him.</hi> And for ſuch ſins God ſends moſt fearefull viſitations. <hi>Icrem.</hi> 5. <hi>Amos</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>Whence this abhominable ſinne doth ſpring is better knowne by bad experience, then by tongue or pen can bee expreſſed. It commonly ſprowts out from the poyſoned root of <hi>bribery;</hi> and therefore they both are ordinarily forbidden in one peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od of ſpeach, by one breath of the Lord:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 16. <hi>v.</hi> 18, 19, 20.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt not reſpect perſons, nor take a gift: for a gift doth blinde the eyes of the wiſe, and peruert the words of the righteous.</hi> and therefore couetouſneſſe, <hi>the roote of all euill,</hi> is the <hi>ſtepmother of iuſtice,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.10.</note> as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> well ſpeakes.</p>
               <p>It ariſeth alſo from many other grounds, as from loue, friendſhip, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred or enuie, wrath, and raſh zeale, impatience, and ſuch like affections and paſſions; which blind the eye, or tranſport the will, ſo farre that the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:3592:42"/>perſon affected therwith doth ſwerue from the rule of equitie and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>Let him put off the robe of a Iudge,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exuat perſonant iudicis qui in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duit ami<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i.</note> 
                  <hi>who putteth on the cloake of a friend;</hi> its <hi>Ciceroes</hi> prouerbiall ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence. <hi>They cannot iudge worthily of ſuch as are vnder them,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dignè de ſubdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis iudicare ne. queunt, qui non merita cauſaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſed perſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rum odium &amp; grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am ſequuntur. Greg. moral.</note> 
                  <hi>who follow not the merit of the cauſes, but the hatred or loue of the perſons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whenceſoeuer it ariſeth or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is the ground of it, ſure it is a great and grieuous ſin, and requires both ſpeedy and exact reformation. For the remedying whereof ſome of former times would haue cauſes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded without <hi>mention</hi> of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: others had their Iudges <hi>couered</hi> with a vaile, that neither plaintiffe not defendant ſhould come in their ſight: others did exerciſe iudgments in the night: others did iudge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Attars</hi> of their <hi>Gods.</hi> But to omit thoſe <hi>heathen</hi> deuices for refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of theſe euils, and that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous example of <hi>Traiane</hi> the <hi>Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror,</hi> of whom it is recorded, that he
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:3592:43"/>
                  <hi>did neuer man wrong in iuſtice, neither at any time had affection or paſsion in giuing iudgment:</hi> we who are <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> haue better grounds of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, namely, the <hi>feare</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>direction</hi> of his <hi>word,</hi> and the <hi>examples</hi> of godly and conſcionable men. Conſider two, of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Samuel,</hi> who could in good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence appeale to the Lord, for the clearing of their vprightneſſe and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrupted integritie; and whom I perſwade my ſelfe you (reuerend Iudges) do religiouſly imitate, and deſire to be like vnto.<note place="margin">Moſes.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord I haue not taken one Aſſe from them</hi> (ſaith <hi>Moſes</hi>) <hi>neither haue I hurt one of them. Deutr.</hi> 16.15. And thus <hi>Samuel</hi> plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth for his integritie:<note place="margin">Samuel.</note> 
                  <hi>Behold here I am</hi> (ſaith he to the people) <hi>witneſſe againſt me before the Lord, and before his annoynted: whoſe Oxe haue I ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken? or whoſe Aſſe haue I taken? or whom haue I defrauded? or whom haue I oppreſſed? or of whom haue I receiued any bribe to blind mine eyes
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:3592:43"/>therewith, and I will reſtore it you. And they ſayd, thou hast not defrau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vs, nor oppreſſed vs, neyther haſt thou taken ought of any mans hand.</hi> Be therefore, &amp; continue ſuch as you ſhould be, and ſuch as I doubt not but you are, <hi>men fearing God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.21.</note> 
                  <hi>and hating couetouſneſſe.</hi> O, let the <hi>feare</hi> of God be in your <hi>hearts,</hi> and theſe godly <hi>examples</hi> before your <hi>eyes,</hi> and pray with <hi>Dauid,</hi> for your ſelues, vnto God.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 26. <hi>v.</hi> 9.10.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord gather not my ſoule with ſinners, nor my life with bloudie men, in whoſe hands is miſchiefe, and their right hand is full of bribes:</hi> And keepe that holie reſolution of <hi>Dauid,</hi> and thus promiſe vnto God; <hi>As for mee I will walke in mine integritie: redeeme mee, and bee mercifull vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The ſecond impediment of juſtice.</note>The other <hi>impediment</hi> and enemie of <hi>iuſtice,</hi> againſt which theſe admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions and cautions are giuen, is <hi>feare</hi> of mens greatneſſe, who will be offended at iuſtice; <hi>yee ſhall not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of the face of Man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:3592:44"/>
Great men are not alwayes good men: and great-good-men, are not (alwayes) ſo good, as not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend or fauor any vnrighteous cauſe. Sometimes they grow partiall in ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of judgement: and if Iudges and miniſters of juſtice be fearefull to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend them, they ſhall hardly deale well for <hi>good</hi> cauſes of <hi>meane</hi> men, for feare of the <hi>perſons</hi> of <hi>great</hi> men.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pilate hearing,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. <hi>19.</hi> v. <hi>12.</hi> In hominum gratiam iuſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am peruertit, &amp; ius inflectit. Pluris facit im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratoris Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mani quam Dei gratiam. Facit contra propriae conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiae teſtimoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, &amp; oris ſui enunciatum.</note> 
                  <hi>and fearing, that</hi> he ſhould not bee accounted <hi>Caeſars friend, if hee ſhould let our Sauiour Chriſt goe,</hi> was ſo quelled with feare, that contrarie to his conſcience and his owne mouthes reſtimonie, he did adiudge our Sauiour Chriſt (though innocent) vnto a ſhamefull and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probrious death. And, ſure it is, this <hi>ſeruile feare</hi> troubles the mind, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracts the thoughts, and corrupts iudgement, and makes the mouth to ſpeak againſt the conſcience, to cleare the wicked, to condemne the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent. And therefore for the preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of ſuch feareful corruption, God
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:3592:44"/>required theſe properties in Iudges, that they ſhould be men of <hi>courage, fearing God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.21. <hi>Prou.</hi> 1.7.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c. The feare of God is the beginning of Wiſedome,</hi> and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of other moſt excellent ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues: Among the reſt, of vndaunted <hi>courage,</hi> and maketh reſolute in good and godly cauſes:<note place="margin">Facile a iuſticiâ deniat qui in cauſis no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſed homines per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timeſcit. Chryſoſt. Pietate ſubla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, fides tollitur. Cicero. Euſeb. de vitâ Conſtant lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>11.</hi> Gen. <hi>20.11.</hi>
                  </note> whereas <hi>hee doth eaſily ſlip aſide from equitie and iustice who stands not in feare of God, but of men ſaith Chryſoſtome.</hi> For <hi>take away pietie, fidelitie is gone:</hi> as we ſee in the <hi>vnrighteous Iudge. Luc.</hi> 18. <hi>v.</hi> 2.3. And as <hi>Conſtantius Chlorus, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Conſtantine the Great,</hi> did well experience in his Counſellors and Courtiers. It was <hi>Abrahams</hi> conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: <hi>The feare of God is not in this place, therefore they will kill me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore (to conclude this) theſe peſtilent impediments of equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and iuſtice, this and the other, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing farre remoued, by Chriſtian cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, feare of God, and hatred of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe, I moſt humbly beſeech you in the name of the Lord, both
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:3592:45"/>Iudges and Magiſtrates, and all mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of iuſtice,<note place="margin">Iſai. <hi>28s</hi> 17.</note> 
                  <hi>Lay iudgement to the rule, and righteouſneſſe to the ballance. Let iudgemet be brought forth in truth, and let the glorie of iuſtice extende it ſelfe like a flowing ſtreame.</hi> Let iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall proceſſe equally proceede in hearing, ſentencing, executing of iudgement without needleſſe protra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and vniuſt delay: and for the better inducing of your godly minds hereunto, conſider the reaſon annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this <hi>Charge, for the iudgement is Gods.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>IV. Point.</hi> Reaſons for obſeruation of the Iniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and Cautions.</note> 
                  <hi>[For the iudgement is Gods]</hi> The reaſon why Iudges and all miniſters of iuſtice ought to performe theſe <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunctions,</hi> and obſerue theſe <hi>cautions,</hi> in iudiciall proceſſe is this; <hi>for the iudgement is Gods:</hi> yea, and to annexe vnto this. that which was premiſed: <hi>The Charge is from God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And to ſpeake hereof but para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſtically for breuities ſake:<note place="margin">The firſt reaſon.</note> 
                  <hi>[The iudgement is Gods]</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1 The <hi>Ordinance</hi> of iudgement
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:3592:45"/>is the ordination of God, by his wiſe and immutable counſell and decree. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. and muſt be vſed faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as the ordinance of God.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The <hi>Perſon</hi> who iudgeth is a perſon ſent of God, by his moſt wiſe and prouident diſpenſation. God made thee a Iudge, Magiſtrate, Iuror, or Witneſſe, by his gracious <hi>ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> or prouident <hi>permiſsion,</hi> and thou muſt deale faithfully as the miniſter of God.</p>
               <p n="3">3 The <hi>Perſon</hi> ſuſtayned by the Iudge is Gods: for he is the <hi>delegate</hi> deputie and miniſter of God: and though for nature, condition, and qualitie, but a man: yet for <hi>title</hi> and <hi>office,</hi> and <hi>authoritie,</hi> a God, and muſt ſquare his iudgement to the will of God.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4 The <hi>cauſes</hi> and <hi>perſons</hi> to bee iudged, are Gods, mans life is Gods, his goods are Gods, the man is Gods, and God is his Father, or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, but ſurely his owner, and muſt be delt well withall, as belonging to God.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:3592:46"/>
5 The iudgement, as (if it be righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous) God did effect it, ſo will hee approue, auow, defend, and reward it. and therefore it muſt bee ſuch as may be auowed of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The ſecond reaſon.</note>And now to end where I firſt did beginne: <hi>The Charge is from God,</hi> for the doing of iuſtice, and he doth enioyne and require the doing of iudgement; and wil one day call to account for what is done, not onely by his <hi>Deputie,</hi> that <hi>little God</hi> of thy <hi>Conſcience,</hi> who wil ſentence thee ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly, if thou doe amiſſe.</p>
               <p>But <hi>he that is higher than the higheſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5.7.</note> the great <hi>God,</hi> and our <hi>Sauiour</hi> Ieſus Chriſt, <hi>the righteous Iudge of quicke and dead,</hi> will iudge thee openly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his dreadfull Tribunal. <hi>God will bring to iudgement euery worke,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Et quid faciet de iniuſtis iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cijs; qui ipſas quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> iuſticias iudicabit, qui cuique merita recitabi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>? Bern. Epiſt.</note> 
                  <hi>with euery ſecret thing, whether it bee good, or whether it bee euill, Eccleſ.</hi> 12.14. And what will he <hi>then doe with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous iudgements, who will then iudge euen iuſtice it ſelfe, who will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite to euery one his owne deſerts?
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:3592:46"/>The Lord of iudgement will come,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Veniet, inquam, veniet Dominus iudicij, vbi plus valebunt pura corda quam aſtuta verba, conſcientia bona quam marſupia plena: vbi iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dex non fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>etur verbis, non fle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctetur donis. <hi>2.</hi> Cor. <hi>5.10.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>will come I ſay, and there pure hearts ſhall preuayle more than ſubtile words, good conſcience than full purſes: when the Iudge ſhall not bee deceiued with wordes, nor ledde with rewards:</hi> but will giue to <hi>euery man according to his workes:</hi> and <hi>euery one ſhall receiue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that he hath done in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, whether it be good or euill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus by Gods gracious aſſiſtance and your Chriſtian attention, I haue ſpoken ſomewhat of the principall parts and paſſages of this charge of God, and the King, to Iudges and Magiſtrates, and all miniſters of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice: as namely, firſt of the inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and iniunctions for right hearing and iudging: ſecondly, of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons whoſe cauſes are to bee heard and iudged: thirdly, of the admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and cautions againſt peſtilent impediments which are frequent e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies to equitie and iuſtice, accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of perſons, and feare of mens faces: fourthly, of reaſons to
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:3592:47"/>enforce the performance of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions and obſeruation of the <hi>cautions?</hi> There onely remaines <hi>the caſe of reſeruation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now that iudiciall proceſſe may bee rightly conformed vnto this charge of God and the King, it muſt be ordered with great counſell and wiſedome, and dependeth much vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the wiſedome and faithfulneſſe of all the miniſters and inſtruments of iuſtice; but lyeth moſt in the wiſe diſcretion and religion of the Iudge; who muſt wiſely conſider all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and circumſtances, for the pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ordering of ſuch important af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, both in matters of controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, and puniſhment of crimes. In both which I would intreat you from the Lord,<note place="margin">In iudiciall proceſſe, two things princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally to bee reſpected.</note> that you would haue moſt ſpeciall regard that there bee mature progreſſe, in iudiciall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe: 2. and alſo equall moderation in puniſhment of malefactors.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">1. Mature pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe.</note>The former of theſe, which I would commend vnto your care, is
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:3592:47"/>mature progreſſe in iudiciall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, in hearing and ſentencing, and executing of ſentence, with all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die diſpatch and conuenient ſpeed, without procraſtination, or vniuſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay.</p>
               <p>The Lord himſelfe enioynes this vnto Iudges. <hi>Deutr.</hi> 25.1. <hi>If there be a controuerſie betweene men, and they come into iudgement, that the iudges may iudge them, then ſhall they iuſtifie the righteous, and condemne the wicked. [Then]</hi> that is, maturely without needleſſe delay. Our <hi>Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our,</hi> in the Parable, doth note it as a marke of an vniuſt Iudge, who is void of all feare of God,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 18.</note> and regard of man, that he deferred to doe iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice to the importunate widdow. Iudges and Magiſtrates muſt in no wiſe bee like <hi>vnhappie Faelix,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 24.27.</note> who left <hi>Paul</hi> in bonds in hope of bribes: but like vnto <hi>Feſtus</hi> his more equall <hi>Succeſſor,</hi> who hearing that <hi>Paul</hi> was kept bound at Ceſaria, promiſed to goe <hi>verie ſhortly</hi> thither, and <hi>the very
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:3592:48"/>next day after his comming thither,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 25.6.</note> conuented him, examined and hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his cauſe, though he fayled in the proceſſe of this buſineſſe, for feare of the Iewes.</p>
               <p>This vniuſt delay of iudiciall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, hath beene an old and auncient corruption: for reformation where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, ſundry <hi>Decrees</hi> were made by thoſe worthie Emperours, <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, Iustinian, Gratian, Valentinian,</hi> and <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> againſt procraſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and dilatory courſes, in matters both of controuerſie and crime.</p>
               <p>In matters of <hi>Controuerſie,</hi> thus <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> doth define.<note place="margin">L. Properandu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> C. de iudicijs Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin. Imperat.</note> 
                  <hi>Properandum nobis viſum eſt ne lites penè fiant im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortales, et vitae hominum modum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedant. In cauſes of controuerſie it ſeemes good to vs that haſt bee made, least cauſes depending become immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, and exceed the meaſure of the life of man.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cauſae pecunia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, et ciuiles omnes, quocun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que nomine ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niant, &amp; cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſcunque ſint quantitatis, non vlterius quam ad tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ennij ſpacium extendi iuben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. ibid.</note> And what a great and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous both ſin and ſhame is it, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in Chriſtian common-wealths, that the <hi>Sonne,</hi> the <hi>aged Sonne,</hi> ſhould
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:3592:48"/>not liue long enough, to ſee an end of the tedious ſuits of his intangled Father, who trode a maze in his end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe proſecution of Law, for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieuing of his ſtill vnrighted wrongs?</p>
               <p>In matters of <hi>Crime,</hi> ſo ſaide the auncient Lawes,<note place="margin">Sic C. L. <hi>1.</hi> de cuſtodia reorum Conſtantinus imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>edicit.</note> 
                  <hi>statim debet quaeſtio fieri, vt noxius puniatur, innocens ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoluatur. Arraignements ought ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily to be made, that the guilty may bee puniſhed, the innocent abſolued:</hi> and againe,<note place="margin">De his quos te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net carcer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſos aperta definitione ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimus, vt aut conuictos velox poena ſubducat, aut liberandos cuſtodiadiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turna non ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceret. Imp. p. p. p. Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian. Valentia. &amp; Theodoſius, decernunt.</note> 
                  <hi>Concerning thoſe who are in priſon, we doe by expreſſe definition e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nact, that eyther ſpeedy puniſhment ſhall make away the</hi> guiltie, or conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall impriſonment ſhall not waſt the innocent.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Our</hi> Lawes no doubt for deciſion of controuerſies are both as perfect and expreſſe as theſe: and therefore is it not a fowle offence, and a feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſinne in any Iudges or Lawyers, or other miniſters of iuſtice, to ſet to ſale their heads and tongues, their wits and words, their places and functions, for the warping and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:3592:49"/>on of the webbe of controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, &amp; protracting of cauſes, through needleſſe delay, for priuate reſpect of gayne, fauour, or enuy; without due regard to common equitie, or publique tranquillitie, or weale and welfare of Church, and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weale.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Reaſons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vniuſt delay of iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note>In this caſe its too true; <hi>Delaye breedes danger:</hi> daunger of <hi>Vndoing</hi> to the partie <hi>oppreſſed:</hi> danger of <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming,</hi> to the perſon <hi>oppreſſing:</hi> danger of hurt to the <hi>party procuring</hi> delay: and danger of <hi>ruine</hi> to Church and Common-weale.</p>
               <p>It grieues the heart,<note place="margin">Reaſ. 1.</note> &amp; excruciates the ſoule of the partie oppreſſed, to beare ſuch a cruell and deteſtable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iury, when vnder plauſible pretence of Law, iudgement, and <hi>iuſtice,</hi> hee is not onely delayed from his right, and ſpends himſelfe in proſecuting for it: but withall incurres ſuſpicion of one wicked and vniuſt, as if hee himſelfe were the doer of the wrong. He that ſhall thus oppreſſe the iuſt
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:3592:49"/>in his righteous cauſe, doth touch the apple of Gods owne eye, which is a fearefull and dangerous ſinne, and prouoketh the Lord to reuenge the oppreſſed.</p>
               <p>Griefe conſtraineth the iuſt,<note place="margin">2</note> who finde no releefe, by iuſt order of law, to take vniuſt and vnlawfull courſes, as calumnies, quarrels, contentions and brawles, to releeue and remedie their vnrighted wrongs; and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, through impotencie of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane affections (eſpecially in wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men more conquerable of paſſions) poyſonings, and murthers of their oppreſſing aduerſaries; and ſo with danger of their lands and goods, they indanger the loſſe both of bodies and ſoules; and ſhall not the vnjuſt occaſioner of ſuch euils communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate in the ſinne, and partake in the miſerie?</p>
               <p>Hereby is a wide flood gate ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and inlarged, whereby hatred,<note place="margin">3</note> contentions and capitall enmities are propagated and diffuſed by part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:3592:50"/>and kindred, ouer whole fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, villages, Cities, Countries, and Kingdomes, which adminiſter mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for mutinies and ſlaughters. <hi>For the contentions of the proud are ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of blood:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sirach.</hi> 27.16.</note> 
                  <hi>and their ſcouldings are greeuous to heare.</hi> And is not hence danger of ruine to the State? And who is the cauſe of all this miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe, but hinderers and peruerters of equitie and inſtice?</p>
               <p>Or if ſuch outward miſchiefe do not hence enſue,<note place="margin">4</note> yet hereby is Gods worſhip and exerciſes of religion (as by an euill ſpirit and helliſh furie of diſcord) diſturbed and poyſoned, while mens minds are diſtracted and exaſperated with continued lawings, and diſſentions: ſo that they can neither heare the word with atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and profit; nor pray priuately or publikely with deuotion or zeale: nor receiue the Sacraments with any quiet or comfort. And ſhall not the vnjuſt hinderers of iudiciall proceſſe, from finall deciding of actions and
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:3592:50"/>controuerſies, ſtand guilty, before the Tribunall of God, as diſturbers of diuine worſhip, and breakers of ſpirituall peace?</p>
               <p>Hereby is iuſtice it ſelfe profanely abuſed,<note place="margin">5</note> and <hi>God</hi> himſelfe the <hi>God of iuſtice,</hi> and preſcriber of equity, moſt impiouſly contemned &amp; monſtrou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly diſhonoured, as if he himſelfe were vnequall or vnjuſt. For when his Delegates and Deputies do per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert judgment, they make God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe (aſmuch as in them lies) to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come author and approuer of their deteſtable impietie.</p>
               <p>All Indges, Counſellors,<note place="margin">6</note> Attour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neyes, Sollicitors, Sheriffes, Iurors or witneſſes, or other miniſters of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, who by corrupt abuſe of Gods ſacred ordinance of iuſtice, open a flood-gate, or window to ſuch enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities and euils, ſhall themſelues be convented (vnleſſe they repent) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the moſt dreadfull Tribunall of God, there to be convicted and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenced for their fearfull offences.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:3592:51"/>
All innocent perſons, who haue bin oppreſſed,<note place="margin">7</note> yet by piety reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from vnjuſt reuenge, and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, by Gods grace, from vnlawfull remedies, ſhall yet in priuate put vp their complaints with ſighes and groanes to the Iudge of Heauen, who as their kind patrone and powerfull protector ſhall take vengeance and puniſhment on ſuch malefactors, as haue not releeued but vnjuſtly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed (and that vnder pretence of law) ſuch helpleſſe ones in their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes and miſeries. The <hi>ſoune</hi> of <hi>Syrach</hi> in his <hi>Eccleſiasticus</hi> (though it be not <hi>Canonicall</hi>) deſcribes this very well,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccleſiaſt.</hi> 35.</note> ſaying.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>v.</hi> 12,</note>
                  <q>The Lord is Iudge and regardeth no mans perſon — but heareth the prayer of the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed.<note place="margin">13.</note> Hee deſpiſeth not the prayer of the fatherleſſe,<note place="margin">14,</note> nor the widow when ſhe powreth out her prayer. Do not the teares runne downe the widowes cheekes?<note place="margin">15.</note> and her cry is againſt him that cauſeth them. (for from her cheekes they
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:3592:51"/>doe go vp to heauen, and the Lord which heareth them doth accept them.</q> Yea the <hi>Lord</hi> in the <hi>Scripture</hi> is frequent in denouncing of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and iudgments on peruerters of iuſtice. <hi>Ier. 5.29. Amos 6.12, 13. Habac.</hi> 1.3, 4, 5. and elſe where.</p>
               <p>Theſe things being ſo (beloued in the Lord) that graue aduice and godly exhortation of King <hi>Iehoſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phat</hi> to Iudges appointed by him, is worthy to be painted on the walls of all Courts and Iudgment-ſeats; yea to be ingrauen in the hearts of all Iudges and Magiſtrates and miniſters of Iuſtice 2 <hi>Chron. 19.6. Take heede what yee do; for yee iudge not for man but for the Lord; who is with you in the iudgment. Wherefore now let the feare of the Lord be vpon you: take heede and do it: for there is no iniquitie with the Lord our God, nor reſpect of perſons, nor taking of gifts.</hi> and remember this charge of the Lord and Moſes: <hi>Heare the cauſes of your brethren and iudge righteouſly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:3592:52"/>
                  <note place="margin">2. Equall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of iuſtice.</note> And thus much of the firſt thing much to be reſpected in iudiciall proceſſe, which is <hi>mature progreſſe,</hi> or ſpeedy proceeding therein: Now followeth the <hi>ſecond,</hi> which is <hi>miti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation or moderation of the ſeueritie of iuſtice.</hi> And to ſpeake of it as far as it extends to the exerciſe of ciuill di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline and puniſhment of malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors. As iudgment muſt proceede according to the preſcript of law: ſo muſt great wiſdome, diſcretion, and religion be vſed that it be ſo gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded between iuſt <hi>clemencie</hi> and need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>ſeueritie,</hi> that the ſentence be equall, and tend to publike good.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Proemijs &amp; poenu. Solon. Quando ciues omnes poenaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> metu à maleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cijs abſtiments, &amp; beneſicioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> praemy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s inritati officium facere ſtude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Demoſt. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> The Common weale (as one well ſaid) is conteined in two things, <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards puniſhments.</hi> and then doth it flouriſh (as another obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) <hi>when all the Citizens or ſubiects thereof abſtaine from cuill-doing for feare of puniſhment, and are invited to do dutie in hope of reward:</hi> and that it may flouriſh, its the dutie of the Magiſtrate to puniſh the bad, and
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:3592:52"/>to reward the good.</p>
               <p>Its rather to be wiſhed than ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, in this our corrupt eſtate, that all would abſtaine from <hi>vice</hi> for <hi>loue</hi> of <hi>vertue,</hi> and <hi>hope</hi> of <hi>reward,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Meliores ſunt quos atrigit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor, ſed plures quos corrigit timor.</note> and for good <hi>conſcience</hi> rather than for <hi>feare</hi> of puniſhment: but ſo ſeruile and vicious is the nature of man, that it hath neede to be curbed and reſtrained from euill, by threat and execution of correction and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and therefore puniſhments are prouided, <hi>that euill ones might be taken out of the way,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vt his tollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur mali ſi eſſe nocentes volin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint, aut emen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentur ſi per ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gligentiam ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid admiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint Sen c. de irâ lib. 1. L riſpiciendum de poenis. Neſp ſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a ſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitas conciom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or, aut vtihor harmonia<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> quam ſeucritas cum comitate co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta. Plutarch. in Phocion.</note> 
                  <hi>if they will needs do harme, or may be amended if through neglect they did amiſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In proceeding to iudgement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt malefactors, mercy and iuſtice muſt meete together, clemencie and ſeueritie muſt kiſſe each other. There muſt be a mercifull <hi>clemencie,</hi> yet ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with <hi>iuſtice,</hi> and a iuſt <hi>ſeueritie,</hi> yet moderated with <hi>equitie,</hi> leſt ſtrict law proue flat iniuſtice: <hi>neither is any ſweetneſſe more ſeemely, or harmonie more profitable, than is ſeueritie ioyned
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:3592:53"/>with humanitie.</hi> Iudgments thus <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derated,</hi> do <hi>pleaſe both God and man.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">— Moderata place<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t hemint<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> deo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Stoickes</hi> aſſertion is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant to <hi>reaſon,</hi> that all ſinnes are equall: nor <hi>Dracoes</hi> bloody lawes conſonant to <hi>iuſtice,</hi> that all crimes are to be puniſhed with death. there are degrees of ſins, and of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: <hi>Spare muſt be made euen of the baſest blood.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pareimonia de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet eſſe etiam viliſſimi ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinis. Senec. de clem: lib. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> Life is deare, death terrible, and the liues of men muſt be precious in their eyes, who deale in matters of life and death. And a <hi>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict</hi> of death muſt not be brought in vpon <hi>ſlight ſuſpicions</hi> and <hi>vncertaine</hi> proofes. <hi>It were better a guilty perſon were cauſleſly abſolued, then that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent ſhould be vniuſtly condemned,</hi> that is a ſinne, but this is impiety, a much more heynous, and more grieuous ſin. Which I deſire the Iurors would looke vnto, who, <hi>not ſeldome,</hi> offend, and that groſsly, in this kind, in bringing within the compaſſe of death, ſuch as of right ought to be acquitted. In this caſe
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:3592:53"/>that rule is ſafe and good:<note place="margin">Placuit in om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus rebus po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiorem eſſe iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae aequitatiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> quam ſtricti iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris rationem. lib. <hi>1.</hi> C. de iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cijs.</note> 
                  <hi>Its better to haue reſpect to iuſtice and equitie than to ſtrict law.</hi> Raſhnes in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning men is to be auoyded: <hi>for he almoſt condemnes willingly that doth it quickly.</hi> and too much ſeueritie muſt euer be abandoned, for he doth <hi>puniſh vniuſtly that puniſheth too much.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet for all this there muſt not be ſuch <hi>clemency</hi> as doth prejudice <hi>equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie:</hi> for ſo, ſin ſhall abound, and if <hi>iuſtice preſſe not the vniuſt, then ſhall the iuſt be oppreſſed with iniuſtice:</hi> and the harmeleſſe, <hi>help-leſſe,</hi> and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent ſheepe ſhall be expoſed to the rage of wolues and rauenors. Too much clemencie breedeth impunitie, and cauſeth liberty and licentiouſnes in ſin. In this caſe the Iudge muſt not be milder than the law: for wholſome ſeueritie, which common reaſon doth ſuggeſt, and publike or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der exacteth, doth excell the vaine ſhew of clemencie &amp; mercy. There is both a puniſhing mercy, and a ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:3592:54"/>cruelty. <hi>Such clemency is but a mercileſſe pitty, as armes malefactors againſt the innocent. He hurts the good that ſpares the bad.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bonis nocet qui malis parcit. ſoſ. Scalig. Non eſt inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manit as ſed po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ma quaedam eſt hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nitas, cum malti paucorum animaduerſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>one ſaluantur.</note> and therefore its well concluded by <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> in his <hi>Nouell Conſtitutions: It is not inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie, but rather ſpeciall humanitie, when many are ſaued by the puniſhment of a few.</hi> Iudgment muſt paſſe with needfull ſeueritie againſt notorious and euident malefactors; as for <hi>trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, poyſonings, murthers,</hi> and the like heynous crimes; <hi>vt poena ad pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cos, metus ad multos perveniat: That puniſhment may fall on a few, feare on many.</hi> For ſome few muſt needs be puniſhed, that more may be terrified, and all may be amended, or reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from euill. This is the ſentence of the Lord himſelfe againſt a falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witneſſe-bearer: <hi>If the witneſſe be a falſe witneſſe, and haue teſtified fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhood against his brother:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deutr.</hi> 19.16, 17, 18, 19, 20</note> 
                  <hi>then ſhall ye do vnto him, as he had thought to haue done vnto his brother. So ſhalt thou put away the euill from among you; and
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:3592:54"/>thoſe which remaine ſhall heare and feare, and from hence-forth ſhall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit no ſuch euill among you. And thy eye ſhall not pitie, but life ſhall go for life</hi> —. and the morall law doth eternally eſtabliſh that the <hi>wilfull murtherer</hi> ſhould die the death.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.6.</note>
               </p>
               <p>I acknowledge indeed that famous Emperors haue bene much admired for clemencie and pitie;<note place="margin">Suet. Veſp.</note> as <hi>Titus Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaſian,</hi> who wept for juſt executions. and whereas the Emperors them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vſed then to iudge of life and death,<note place="margin">Tranquill, in Tito.</note> he was hardly drawne to giue iudgment at all, and vtterly <hi>vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> to condemne any to death. <hi>Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricius,</hi> who by his good will would not haue ſo much as a Traytor die.<note place="margin">Euagr. l. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> in prudence ſecond to none, yet being to examine a parri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide, began thus:<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an. Bod. de rep. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Certè patrem non occidisti:</hi> Surely thou haſt not ſlaine thy father. In which words he did not onely inſtruct the guilty perſon what he ſhould anſwer to the Prince and Iudge, but alſo in admirable hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:3592:55"/>did pardon the parricide. <hi>Theodoſius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Socr. lib. <hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>22.</hi>
                  </note> who was wont to wiſh that he could recall to life ſuch as had wronged him. <hi>Nero</hi> himſelfe, otherwaies cruell, who being asked to ſubſcribe to a ſentence of death, gaue this anſwer, <hi>Vtinam liter as neſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem,</hi> I would I could not tell how to write.</p>
               <p>But be it granted that Clemency is a princely vertue (as the King of Bees is without a ſting) and Bounty another,<note place="margin">Nihil eſt quod Imperatorem meliùs commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dat gentibus, quam Clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia. Antoninus ad Coniugem. Valcatius in vita Caſſij.</note> which winnes much loue: for which cauſe <hi>Titus Veſpaſian</hi> was accounted the loue and delight of mankind: yet exceſſe herein is no vertue but a vice, when it hinders the current of needfull execution of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice. And nothing is ſo contrary to the office of a Iudge as ſuch mercy, when the Iudge becomes more mild than law in ſparing the execution of notorious malefactors. Such impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of groſſe offences, is (as one ſaith) a moſt certaine argument of the periſhing eſtate of a Common-wealth.
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:3592:55"/>Puniſhments duely execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted are the ſinewes of the weale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publike.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſthenes.</note>
               </p>
               <p>True, indeed, in caſes of difficultie there muſt be inclination to <hi>mercy.</hi> In leſſer offences (once or ſeldome committed) mitigation of <hi>ſeueritie. Frequenter qui peccant &amp; lugent, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam vix merentur: Such as often offend though they mourne for their fault, yet ſcarce deſerue pardon</hi> ſaith <hi>Auguſtine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And Chriſtian compaſſion in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueritie of cenſure commiſerating the miſery of a guilty perſon, beſeemes a Chriſtian Iudge, who (when he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth the ſentence of death) may with <hi>Auguſtus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Seneca in lib. de Clementia.</note> 
                  <hi>ex imo pectore ſuſpiria ducere;</hi> fetch deepe ſighes from the bottom of his heart, and be more ſorry for them, than they are for themſelues: yet law muſt haue courſe, iuſtice muſt be done, that euill may thereby be taken away, that others that heare may feare, and doe no more ſo preſumptuouſly; and
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:3592:56"/>that the land ſtand not before God guilty of blood: leſt Gods ſword be vnſheathed, and his hand ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the reuenging of ſo great and ſo ſinfull conniuencies, when impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie is permitted to bloody crying finnes. In few words to conclude this point: As thoſe Iudges or Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates are not to be imitated, who in acerbitie of puniſhments affect the opinion of ſeueritie: ſo neither thoſe who by too much facilitie ſeeke loue and affect the opinion of lenitie. Both theſe are faults in the extreme, ſwaruing from the office of a Iudge,<note place="margin">l. reſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>iendum de poenis.</note> as auncient lawes do teach and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare. Equitie walkes in the golden meane betweene rigorous ſeueritie which puniſheth any too much; and cruell mercy which ſpareth a few to the hurt of many.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Application of the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine to ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry orders of Perſons.</note>Now it remaineth that I ſhould apply this charge, for iuſtice, of God and the King, giuen by Moſes to the Iudges of Iſrael, to our Honorable and Reuerend Iudges here preſent:
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:3592:56"/>neither to our Reuerend Iudges alone, but to all thoſe miniſters and inſtruments of iuſtice (ſundry per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of different qualitie) who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre as aſſiſtants in the diſpatch of this buſines. But becauſe my ſpeach hath already paſſed the bounds of the allotted time, I ſeeme vrged by neceſſitie to forbeare the ſame, and to commend the particular applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof, to your priuate, deuout and godly meditations. yet hoping your wiſdomes will redeeme a litle time, by cutting off ſome leſſer occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; I will make bold to ſpeake a litle to the principall of thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, whom this charge doth ſo neer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concerne.</p>
               <p>My Honorable Lords, you the reuerend Iudges of theſe Aſſizes,<note place="margin">1 To Iudges.</note> I ſhall not need to ſpeake much vnto you: becauſe the Lord in mercy hath beſtowed vpon you (to ſpeake (as I am well perſwaded) without flatterie) a great meaſure of wiſdom &amp; piety to deale in matters of iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:3592:57"/>iuſtly and conſcionably, and you haue right well approued both to King and Country your fidelitie and ſinceritie in execution of your function; in ſo much as we bleſſe God for you, and pray to God to bleſſe you, that you alſo may conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue a bleſſing vnto vs. Yet giue me leaue to put you in minde of this your charge from God &amp; the King: Heare the cauſes between your bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and iudge righteouſly. Your wiſdome and long experience haue taught you well, that that of <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome</hi> is very true: <hi>Ipſam cauſae inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nire iuſtitiam grande opus:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>3.</hi> de Sacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotali dignit. cap. <hi>18.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>inventam verò nulla iniquitate corrumpere labo rioſiſsimum: To find out the very iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of the cauſe is a great worke.</hi> and therefore you had need to be very circumſpect therein. and <hi>when its once found out, then to corrupt it by no iniquitie is a moſt laborious thing,</hi> and therefore you had neede to be very vpright therein.</p>
               <p>And that I may ioyne with the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:3592:57"/>reuerend Iudges, thoſe worthie ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates,<note place="margin">2. To Iuſtices of Peace.</note> the Iuſtices of Peace: you well vnderſtand what a fearefull ſin it is <hi>to turne iudgement into Worme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Amos.</hi> 5.7.</note> 
                  <hi>and to leaue of righteouſneſſe in the Earth.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ames</hi> 6.12.</note> 
                  <hi>To turne iudgement into gall, and the fruit of righteouſneſſe into Wormewood.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ier.</hi> 5.28.</note> 
                  <hi>To ouerpaſſe the deedes of the Wicked, to execute no iudgement, no not the iudgement of the fatherleſſe, to execute no iudgement for the poore.</hi> What a fearefull ſinne were it for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of you to ſuffer through your neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect or partiality, <hi>iust iudgement ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to goe forth:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.4.</note> 
                  <hi>but the wicked to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe about the righteous, and wrong iudgement to proceed?</hi> Theſe are feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſinnes in Iudges and magiſtrates, for which the Lord did ſharpely threaten, and ſeuerely puniſh his owne people.</p>
               <p>Wherefore, I earneſtly beſeech you from the Lord, continue ſtill, if you haue begun, <hi>to be men of courage, fearing God, dealing truely,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 18. <hi>Eſay.</hi> 1.17.</note> 
                  <hi>and hating couetouſneſſe.</hi> And <hi>ſeeke iudgement,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:3592:58"/>relieue the oppreſſed, iudge the father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, and defend the widow,</hi> that you may ſafely preuent ſuch fearefull ſin and wofull miſerie.</p>
               <p>Your calling is honourable, ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of God, as a ſoueraigne antidote againſt euill, and promoter of good: Your perſons are ſelected to this function by God. The perſon you ſuſteine is the Sonne of God, who hath honoured you with the title and authoritie of God, who is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent as chiefe Preſident in the aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of Gods. Your iudgement which you giue, is the iudgement of God, and he will auow, and defend both it and you, if it be iuſt: hee will renounce both it and you, if by your wit, or will, it be vnjuſt, as vnbeſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming his Maieſtie, who is iuſtice it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">3 To Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors.</note>You the Aduocates of juſtice, as Counſellors and Pleaders; I beſeech you to endeuour in the feare of God to cleare your ſelues of thoſe two im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations which ſometimes are layd
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:3592:58"/>vpon ſome of you: how iuſtly vpon any of you that are preſent, not I, but God and your owne conſciences can tell you: namely firſt, that there is no cauſe ſo bad, but by your ſhifts and pretences you can make it ſeeme good: ſecondly, nor no cauſe ſo good, but by your vnskilfulneſſe or vnfaithfulneſſe in handling, you can make it ſeeme bad.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Turpe eſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendere quod non mihi conſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terit iuſtum eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe. Gregor.</note>Conſider (I beſeech you) that it is a verie fowle thing reſolutely to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend what cauſe you know not to be iuſt: but when you perceiue &amp; know it to be vniuſt, then by querkes and deuiſes to cloake and ouer-ſhadow falſehood, and wrong, and (againſt conſcience) to out-face both truth and iuſtice, in the face of the Court, and Iudgement-Seat, before Gods Miniſter of Iuſtice, yea, God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, it is a moſt horrible and feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſinne. This were to call <hi>good, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill; and euill, good:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſa.</hi> 5.18.</note> 
                  <hi>to instifie the wicked for a reward, and to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the righteouſneſſe of the righteous
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:3592:59"/>from him: yea to draw iniquitie with cords of vanitie, and ſinne as with cart-ropes.</hi> Againſt which manie fearefull woes are denounced. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member (I pray you) that worthie example of the learned and vpright Lawyer <hi>Papinian,</hi> who being deſired by the Emperour <hi>Antoninus Cara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calla,</hi> to defend his <hi>fratricide</hi> of his brother <hi>Geta,</hi> anſwered boldly:<note place="margin">Spartian.</note> 
                  <hi>Non tam facile eſt excuſare fratricidiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quam facere.</hi> Its not ſo eaſie to defend fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricide, as to doe it. And he would rather dye, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vndertake the defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of an vniuſt and vnrighteous cauſe.</p>
               <p>And if you haue taken on you the defence of a good cauſe, doe not by your ignorance ouer-throw it, or by your vnfaithfulneſſe betray it, and make your poore client pay ful dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for your ouerſight in formes of proſecution.</p>
               <p>But be aduertiſed (I pray you) by vertue of this charge, to heare and iudge righteouſly. Informe your ſelues throughly in the ſtate of the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:3592:59"/>cauſe, and deale faithfully with your Client in relating what you thinke of the equitie of the cauſe, and iſſue of the controuerſie. And if it bee bad, let it not by any your meanes be proſecuted with coſt, loſt with infamie, or wonne by iniquitie, and flat injuſtice.</p>
               <p>If good, let it not want good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, by your neglect or ouerſight, or want of countenance and fidelitie in pleading: or become more coſtly, by your procraſtinations. But vſe your beſt endeauour, that right may be found with moderate expenſes: that law may proue a ſpeciall and ſpeedy remedy of wrongs, and not a trap or engine to catch and inſnare men; as men of all ſorts doe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly complayne. Then though your poore Client doe not enrich you with his fees, yet ſhall you bee no looſers when you haue made vp your reckonings; but what is wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the poore Clients ſmall fees, ſhall God himſelfe recompence in
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:3592:60"/>your great accounts, and beſtow vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you not a temporall garland, but an eternal crowne of glorie for your vertue and well-doing to the people of God.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">4. To Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes.</note>You Witneſſes, who ſhall for true teſtimonie to the truth, take a ſolemne oath of God and the King, and calling vpon the glorious name of God, vow damnation to your ſoules, if you ſpeake not truth. Know that a feareful curſe is gone out from the Lord, vpon all ſuch as ſhall ſo ſolemnely take his glorious name in vaine.</p>
               <p>A falſe Swearer is guilty two waies,<note place="margin">Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſoſs. in mat <hi>5.</hi> &amp; eſt. <hi>22.</hi> q <hi>5.</hi> cau. quicunque.</note> both becauſe he takes Gods name in vaine, and becauſe he takes his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour by deceit: yea a falſe witneſſe is obnoxious, and offends againſt God, whom hee contemneth; the Iudge, whom he ſeduceth; the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, whom he wrongeth by his falſe teſtimonie; yea, to his family, which he hurteth; and to his owne Soule, which he condemneth.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:3592:60"/>
O be not (I beſeech you) ſo tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous to God, ſo treacherous to the Iudge, ſo iniurious to your brethren, ſo hurtfull to your poſteritie, ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperately prodigall of the bloud of your owne ſoules, as hauing layed them to God for pawnes of truth, you will wittingly, and willingly, ſweare, and forſweare, againſt God and truth, King and Iudge, neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and familie, and your owne ſelues, as lewd, and godleſſe, and graceleſſe ſonnes of <hi>Belial.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But beeing called hither by God and the King, to this ſeruice of your Countrey (all you that haue taken or are to take an oth) <hi>ſweare in truth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ier.</hi> 4.22.</note> 
                  <hi>in iudgement, and righteouſneſſe.</hi> Theſe three, if they be wanting, its not ſo much an oath as a perjurie. Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge your oathes vnto the Lord. Be not ſo ſilly as not to conceiue the truth: nor ſo forgetfull as not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member truth: nor ſo ſubtile as to deceiue both others and your ſelues by falſe witneſſe-bearing againſt the
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:3592:61"/>truth. Know what you teſtifie: te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie what you know. The whole truth, and nothing but the truth. The whole truth: be not afraid of the face of any great man, who may ſit on your skirts for ſpeaking the truth. Nothing but the truth: doe not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept mens perſons in iudgement. Be not corrupted with friendſhip, nor ſuborned with reward. Shake off vaine feare, caſt off vaine hope. Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for ſmall aſwell as for great: for Stranger aſwell as for brother: giue a playne teſtimonie to truth and veritie: So ſhall you haue the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of honeſtie for your credite among men: The teſtimony of good conſcience for comfort in your ſelues: and teſtimonie from Chriſt at the day of the great Aſſiſe, as fit to inhabite in his holy mountaine for euer.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>5.</hi> To Queſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and Iurors.</note>The charge of God and the King to all Queſt-men, and Iurors, is the ſame in effect with that of the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, that they heare and giue ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:3592:61"/>righteouſly, diſcharging their oathes vnto the Lord.</p>
               <p>Far be it from you (my brethren) to be ſuch as ſome common Iurors are, of ſome, ſaid to be; ſo quicke of conceit, as that they know the caſe before they heare it, &amp; ſo readie of reſolution, that they know which way their verdict ſhall goe, aſſoone as they know the partie whom they would pleaſure or pleaſe, to bee the plaintife, or the defendant, before the cauſe bee opened, or euidence produced. But as the Law doth preſume you to bee Gentlemen of choyce for wiſedome and integritie, and yeomen of good note for truth and honeſtie, experienced in Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, and caſes to bee tryed: ſo be diligent in ſifting and examming all proofes and euidences, readie to conceiue and acknowledge apparant equitie, and conſcionable in bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in an approued verdict, not par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall nor vnequall in hope of reward, or for feare of daunger: for fauour
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:3592:62"/>to your friends, or enuy to your ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries: but ſuch as may be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of God and men, to your cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite and comfort, and the publique good.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, you, my brethren, the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of the Countrey,<note place="margin">6. To the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the Countrey.</note> who ſeeke in theſe places of iudgement, the face the Iudge, to haue your cauſes tryed in matters of controuerſie; or elſe are brought hither to be iudged in matters of crime. Follow peace with all men, and holineſſe, without which no man ſhall ſee the Lord. Whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer you would that men ſhould do vnto you, euen ſo doe yee to them.</p>
               <p>For matter of crime,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.17. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.13. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.11.</note> take thoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortations: Feare God: honour the King: Eſchew euill, and doe good: Practiſe pietie toward God, equitie toward men: Liue holily as good Chriſtians in a Chriſtian Church: liue blameleſſely as good ſubiects in a Chriſtian Common-wealth. Auoid thoſe capitall crimes, and ſhamefull courſes, which bring men to cenſure
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:3592:62"/>before theſe iudgement ſeats. And, to ſpeake particularly,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.3.</note> If thou wilt not bee afraid of the power of the magiſtrate, doe that which is good, and thou ſhalt haue prayſe of the ſame, whoſoeuer thou art. But if thou doe euill, then be afraid; for he bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not the ſword in vaine: for hee is the miniſter of God, a reuenger to execute wrath vpon him which doth euill. Art thou then a traytor to the King or Common-wealth, a wilfull murtherer or poyſoner of thy brother: Then the ſword of iuſtice muſt be ſheathed in thy bloud, that euill may be taken away: that the land be not guilty of thy foule of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence: that others may heare and feare: that ſinne may bee puniſhed in thee, and preuented in other that heare or ſee thee.</p>
               <p>If thou receiue cenſure for ſome ſmaller offence, learne by this thy cenſure to amend thy life, leſt a worſe thing hereafter befall thee; for thy iterating of thy ſinne, will
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:3592:63"/>increaſe thy puniſhment.</p>
               <p>In caſe of controuerſie, I beſeech you all to obſerue theſe rules: ſeeke peace, and follow after it: follow peace with all men. Defraud not one another.<note place="margin">Publicè intereſt vt lites iniuſtae at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> inanes co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erceantur; ne Magiſtratus querelis atque cauſis nihil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupetur, neue ciues temerè iuter ſe rixen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, pacemque turbent. L. <hi>21.</hi> ff. ſi certum petatur.</note> And if controuerſies ariſe, vſe all good meanes for the ſpeedie compounding of them, that the Iudgement-ſeat be not troubled with euery trifling brawle, and need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſuite.</p>
               <p>And whereas none are more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die than you to cry out of Lawyers, Atturneys, and ſuch men, as vncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionable in peruerting of iuſtice, as vnreaſonable extortioners, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torters of fees, as defrauders and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doers of the Common-weale: ſcra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping to themſelues the fat of the land &amp;c. Take heed that the fault and cauſe of theſe euils, doe not firſt iſſue and ſpring out from your ſelues; from your peeuiſh and wrongfull and reuengefull diſpoſitions. Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer thou art therefore that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playneſt of others, take heed leſt the
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:3592:63"/>fault be found in thy ſelfe. Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute no bad cauſe, of hatred to hurt another, but onely good cauſes, and that of neceſſitie to relieue thy ſelfe. Packe no Iuries. Suborne no witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. Bribe no Iudges, Lawyers, nor miniſters of juſtice: vſe no calumnies, forgeries, or vnjuſt protractions, or vn-warrantable practiſes for the effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting of thy purpoſes in vnlawfull proceedings: for if it fall out thou be juſtly caſt in thy bad cauſe, then ſhalt thou beare an heauie burden of iuſt puniſhment for thy wilfull pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of thy vnrighteous ſuit. Or if by force or fraud thou preuayle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt equitie, then (which is worſe) thou burdeneſt thy ſelfe with the fearefull guilt of double iniquitie. And though thou get the day in the place of iudgement on earth; yet ſhalt thou looſe the day at Gods Iudgement-ſeat in Heauen.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Application to all ioyntly.</note>And now at length to grow to a finall concluſion of all; theſe things being ſo; as <hi>Iehoſaphat</hi> that moſt
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:3592:64"/>worthy ſeruant of God did charge thoſe Iudges whom he had made: ſo do I a poore Miniſter of Chriſt, in the name of the Lord charge you all that haue the leaſt finger in matters of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice (as Reuerend Iudges, worthy Iuſtices, Counſellors, Iurors, witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and the reſt) <hi>Take heed what yee doe:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.6.7.</note> 
                  <hi>for yee iudge not for man, but for the Lord, who is with you in the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Wherefore now let the feare of the Lord be vpon you, take heed and do it: for there is no iniquitie with the Lord our God, nor reſpect of perſons, nor taking of gifts.</hi> And as <hi>Moſes</hi> to theſe Iudges of Iſrael in this place: <hi>Heare the cauſes between your brethren and iudge righteouſly betweene euery man and his brother, and the ſtranger that is with him. Yee ſhall not reſpect perſons in iudgement; but you ſhall heare the ſmall aſwell as the great. you ſhall not be afraid of the face of man:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">V. and laſt poynt. Of reſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> 
                  <hi>for the iudgment is Gods.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now I ſhould proceed to the <hi>caſe of reſeruation: And if the cauſe be
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:3592:64"/>too hard for you bring it vnto me, and I will heare of it.</hi> But of this I ſay no more but this. That whereas theſe cauſes and matters of iudgment are farre too great for any of vs, who of our ſelues cannot thinke a good thought: Therefore let vs appeale to God, and to his Throne of grace for his aſſiſtance and bleſſing in theſe weighty affaires of Iudgment.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O bleſſed Lord God, Father of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and God of all grace, graunt (we humbly intreat thee) to our Iudges and Magiſtrates, heauenly wiſdom, chriſtian courage, godly feare, vncorrupted inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritie in hearing and iudging: to all the miniſters and inſtruments of iuſtice and equitie, vprightnes and good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in proſecuting and promoting of actions and cauſes: to all the people louing affections and peaceable diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions one toward another, thankfulnes vnto thee for this thine ordinance of iudgement, and dutiful obedience to the rules of pietie, iustice, and equitie: that ſo vice may be puniſhed, vertue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged:
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:3592:65"/>iniuſtice may be remoued, equitie maintained: The common-wealth may be proſpered, the Church en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged; our poore ſoules may be ſaued, and thy great name glorified, in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation of thine aboundant mercie in our felicitie: and that for the merits of thine onely Sonne, and our onely Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Ieſus Chriſt, the righteous Iudge of quicke and dead; to whom with Thee, O Father, and with thy Holie-Spirit, three glorious Perſons, but one only true and euer-liuing God, be aſcribed of vs, and of thy whole Church, all Honour, Glorie, Praiſe, Power, Maieſtie, Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and Thankes-giuing, from this time forth for euer-more: Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <hi>All glorie be to</hi> GOD.</closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:3592:65"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
